<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The womans glorie a treatise, asserting the due honour of that sexe, and directing wherein that honour consists : dedicated to the young princesse, Elizabeth her highnesse / by Samuel Torshel.</title>
            <author>Torshell, Samuel, 1604-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 122 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2556</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12129916</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12129916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54709</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62975)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54709)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 900:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The womans glorie a treatise, asserting the due honour of that sexe, and directing wherein that honour consists : dedicated to the young princesse, Elizabeth her highnesse / by Samuel Torshel.</title>
                  <author>Torshell, Samuel, 1604-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 232 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for Iohn Bellamie ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  History --  Modern period, 1600-</term>
               <term>Manners and customs.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54709:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54709:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Womans Glorie. A TREATISE, ASSERTING The due Honour of that SEXE, AND Directing wherein that Honour conſiſts.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to the young Princeſſe, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her Highneſſe.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Torſhel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamie,</hi> at the three golden Lions near the Royall Exchange. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:54709:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54709:2"/>
            <head>To the Excellent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, a Lady of great hopes and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation Princeſſe ELIZABETH <hi>Her Highneſse.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the <hi>Honour,</hi> and for a publike teſtimonie of your more then ordinary <hi>Pregnancie</hi> and <hi>Capable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in ſo young and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yeares, I have now dedicated to your <hi>Name,</hi> what I prepared eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for your uſe, and for the ſervice of your <hi>grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:54709:3"/>vertues. Reade</hi> over again, what you heard, and in part noted with your own <hi>Pen.</hi> Strive to anſwer your hopefull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, that you may riſe to be <hi>the glory of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſses.</hi> This ſhall be a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> for after yeares, what you were at <hi>nine yeares of age,</hi> that hereafter it may <hi>praiſe</hi> your encreaſe, or <hi>admoniſh</hi> you, if it be otherwiſe. However it ſhall remain as a witneſſe of the <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highneſs's moſt humble Servant.</hi> SAM. TORSHE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54709:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou will pleaſe to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that the occaſion of this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> was a <hi>Sermon,</hi> or <hi>Exhortation,</hi> which I made at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> the <hi>28.</hi> of December laſt, which day we kept in remembrance of the birth of Princeſſe <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> ſecond daughter to our <hi>King;</hi> If cuſtome, and the <hi>due reſpect</hi> we owe to the branches of the <hi>Royall
<pb facs="tcp:54709:4"/>Familie</hi> had not prevailed with us, yet the great hopes and the very <hi>bloſſomes</hi> of vertue and other excellent parts in this <hi>Princeſſe</hi> would have commanded from us all this <hi>Reſpect.</hi> I have now ſomewhat inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged what I then ſpake, and have ſitted it into a <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</hi> My main end in it, is only to advance the <hi>worke</hi> that is properly in my <hi>hand,</hi> to bring in ſome, if it may be, and to build them up in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe.</hi> The Lord ſanctifie all meanes to this purpoſe, and <hi>Crowne</hi> every endeavour with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: I have purpoſely la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured
<pb facs="tcp:54709:4"/>a <hi>familiar plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> as aiming at <hi>benefit,</hi> not <hi>delight.</hi> And I ſhall deſire of all that ſhall reade it, to bring <hi>ſerious</hi> thoughts, and free from <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice</hi> or <hi>lightneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:54709:5"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Chap. 1. <hi>Women capable of the higheſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements. They were made after the Image of God The Sout the ſame. Their bodies as orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall. The whole Sexe unduty reproached.</hi> pag. 1</item>
               <item>Chap. 2. <hi>Some Inſtances of eminencie in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> 1. <hi>Wiſdome. Policie. Deliberation. Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</hi> 2. <hi>Learning.</hi> p. 16.</item>
               <item>Ch. 3. <hi>The Letters touching this argument, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween</hi> And. River, <hi>&amp;</hi> A. Maria <hi>à</hi> Schurma. p 34</item>
               <item>Chap. 4. <hi>Other Inſtances of womens eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi> 3. <hi>Conſtancie.</hi> 4. <hi>Courage.</hi> 5. <hi>Abilitie to govern.</hi> 6. <hi>Piety and Religion.</hi> pag. 74</item>
               <item>Chap. 5. <hi>Soule glory is chiefeſt. What Soule glory or Inward beautie is</hi> pag. 95</item>
               <item>Ch. 6. <hi>Modeſtie proper to women. Modeſty of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, Of la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage. A ceaſure of lewd books.</hi> p. 110</item>
               <item>Chap. 7. <hi>The former grace commended. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie in Attire.</hi> pag. 128</item>
               <item>Chap 8. <hi>Humility, a Grace of great Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Womens Subjection. The queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther women may be Teachers.</hi> pag. 142</item>
               <item>Chap. 9. <hi>The Excellencie of Wiſdome. The uſefuln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> The Maximet of Wiſdom.</hi> p. 102</item>
               <item>Chap. 10. <hi>Stence a great proofe of Wiſdome. The hatefulneſſe of Diſsimulation.</hi> p. 182</item>
               <item>Chap. 11. <hi>The beautie of holineſse. The rule of Devotion. A ſerious exhortation to the realing of the Scripture.</hi> p. 195</item>
               <item>Chap. 12. <hi>The Maximes of Pietie. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</hi> p. 218</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54709:5"/>
            <head>THE Womans Glorie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Women capable of the higheſt improvements. They were made after the Image of God. The Soul the ſame. Their bodies as organicall. The whole Sexe unduly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Reader</hi> in the <hi>Porch,</hi> but let him in without ceremonie into the <hi>Points,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54709:6"/>which I have undertaken, which are theſe two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That Women are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the higheſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test glory to which man may be advanced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That their higheſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement is that of the Soul, and their greatest glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is Soul-glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know the <hi>Subject</hi> that I have now <hi>entertained,</hi> may become the <hi>diſcourſe</hi> of <hi>light</hi> and <hi>vain wits;</hi> but let them know that theſe <hi>Points</hi> are held forth in the <hi>Sacred Scriptures,</hi> where we have the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels and mind of God;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54709:6"/>and I ſhall ſo ſpeake of them, as may become both the <hi>ſevere Majeſtie</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>ſeriouſneſſe</hi> of my owne <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Office.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That women are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the highest improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the greateſt glory to which man may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might call in the <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies</hi> of the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> of the <hi>Heathens</hi> concerning this; among others I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Plutarch</hi> one of the moſt learned of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> upon the death of the excellent <hi>Leontide,</hi> diſcourſed with his friend
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54709:7"/>of the <hi>equall vertue</hi> of man and woman, and doubts not if he might compare <hi>lives</hi> with <hi>lives,</hi> and <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> with <hi>actions,</hi> to make it to appeare, that as <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho's</hi> verſes were equall with <hi>Anacreon's,</hi> ſo <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miramis</hi> was as <hi>magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> as <hi>Seſostris,</hi> Queen <hi>Tanaquilla</hi> as <hi>politique</hi> as King <hi>Servius,</hi> and <hi>Porcia</hi> as full of courage as <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> But though I will not refuſe the <hi>light</hi> that is brought in by ſuch <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> and the <hi>examples</hi> upon record in their <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> becauſe much of the workmanſhip and power
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54709:7"/>of God is ſeen even in them. Yet I will princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally build upon <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Grounds</hi> and <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> from whom we receive the firſt and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall truths, tels us that <hi>woman</hi> as well as <hi>man</hi> was created after the Image of God.
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.27.</note> 
                  <hi>God created man in his owne Image, in the Image of God created he him, male and female crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he them.</hi> What the Image of God is, and what the difference (if there be any) is between <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Similitude,</hi> I am not diſputing; this is it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54709:8"/>for which I have allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Moſes,</hi> that <hi>woman</hi> hath the ſame preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of creation with <hi>man.</hi> If <hi>man</hi> were endowed (as he was) with a ſpirituall, rationall, free, willing, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Soul: ſo was <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> If there were (as there was) a <hi>rectitude</hi> in <hi>man,</hi> ſo that there was in his mind a right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods nature, will, and workes; and in his will, appetites, moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and actions, a ſweet Conformity and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with God: So there was in <hi>woman.</hi> If <hi>man</hi> were put (as he was) into a ſtate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54709:8"/>of dominion and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſo was <hi>woman.</hi> Let <hi>Divines</hi> agree it among themſelves, whether all this, or more then this, were meant by the <hi>Image of God,</hi> whatſoever they ſhall eſtate upon <hi>man,</hi> the <hi>woman</hi> will alſo challenge by that authentick Text. By which Text alſo we muſt be guided in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> in ſome paſſages of his in the eleventh Chap. of the firſt Epiſt. to the <hi>Corinths.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>That the head of every man is Chriſt, and the head of the woman is the man.</hi> Which he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54709:9"/>ſpeakes not putting a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in their creation, but of that ſubordination which was afterwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, when God ſaid to <hi>Eve,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16.</note> Thy deſire ſhall be to thy husband, and he ſhall rule over thee.</hi> And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of this Subjection he ſaith further, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>That man is the image and glorie of God, but the woman is the glorie of the man, for the man is not of the woman, but the woman of the man; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was the man created for the woman, but the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for the man.</hi> 'Tis true that from the beginning, the woman was ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54709:9"/>as in order of time ſhe was created after man: and being intended to be an helper, ſhe ſhines moſt, when ſhe doth moſt obſerve that Ordinance of Subjection, for then ſhe is <hi>the glorie of the man,</hi> according to the inſtance of the prudent woman that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes of,
<note place="margin">Prov. 31.11, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>In whom the heart of her husband doth ſafely truſt;</hi> and ſhe being modeſt and induſtrious, <hi>Her husband is knowne in the gates, when he ſitteth among the Elders of the Land.</hi> Yet ſhe loſeth not her firſt Right, of which the Apoſtle being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54709:10"/>tender, addeth in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth verſe, <hi>Nevertheleſse neither is the man without the woman, neither the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man without the man, in the Lord.</hi> Both were made by the ſame hand, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame <hi>Idea:</hi> ſo moſt doe underſtand that phraſe, <hi>In the Lord,</hi> which interpretation ſecures the <hi>point</hi> for which <hi>Moſes</hi> was alleadged. But if we take it as others doe, that by the <hi>Lord</hi> is meant, The <hi>Lord Christ,</hi> the point will receive an improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That as <hi>man</hi> and <hi>woman</hi> were equall in Creation, ſo there is no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54709:10"/>difference between them in <hi>ſtate of Grace.</hi> Which truth, whether it be held forth in this place or not, I will not contend; for elſewhere we have it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, that <hi>there is neither male nor female,</hi> no prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of one ſex before the other,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.28</note> 
                  <hi>but all one in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Soul</hi> knowes no difference of <hi>Sexe,</hi> as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe the <hi>Angels,</hi> and therefore it is that ſome learned men are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that after the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in the ſtate of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, there will be no more
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54709:11"/>any diſtinction of <hi>male</hi> and <hi>female,</hi> becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.30. <hi>We ſhall then be as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God in heaven.</hi> And the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42, 43, 44. That <hi>the body being ſowne</hi> (in the grave) <hi>in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, in diſhonour, in weakneſſe, ſhall be raiſed in incorruption, in glory, in power.</hi> The commerce of <hi>Sexes,</hi> was of neceſſitie becauſe of corruption and change by mortalitie. But the body that ſhall be raiſed, in difference from the naturall body, is called <hi>A Spirituall body.</hi> The Soul then knowing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54709:11"/>no ſubordination becauſe of <hi>Sexe,</hi> as for the reſt, the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>woman</hi> is made <hi>organicall,</hi> like that of <hi>mans,</hi> as to the <hi>Soul,</hi> ſo that there is nothing that puts a barre to the Souls operations. There dwell in them the ſame <hi>Deſires</hi> and <hi>Breathings,</hi> and they are indowed with the ſame faculties and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>They are heires toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with men of the grace of life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.7.</note> They have the ſame right of Adoption, and are under the ſame benefit of purchaſe, and therfore are gifted by the ſame ſanctifying Spirit.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54709:12"/>
               <p>I know that many of the <hi>Antients</hi> have ſpoken much to the <hi>leſſening</hi> and the <hi>reproach</hi> of the whole <hi>Sexe;</hi> as that they are weak in Councell
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſt. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. lib</hi> 1.</note>, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in courage
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Hypocrat Aphor.</hi> § 7. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>Plin. nat. Hiſt. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c,</hi> 17.</note>, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame and inordinate in their affections, mutable and uncertaine in their wils, unfit to rule and manage affaires. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly not only the <hi>Parthians</hi> and <hi>Thracians</hi> accounted them and uſed them as ſlaves, but the <hi>Greekes</hi> deſpiſed
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Homer</hi> cals the <hi>Achaians, Achaides,</hi> becauſe they gav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the rule to women.</note> them, and the <hi>Civill Romanes</hi> made Lawes in prejudice of their reputation, which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54709:12"/>were ſome of them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards inſerted into the <hi>Edicts</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Emperours;</hi> Some calling the <hi>Government</hi> of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men a <hi>prevarication of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> Some <hi>lawes</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to them <hi>Tutors</hi> and <hi>Guardians,</hi> though when of growne age, yea, even to widowes.</p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding all this <hi>prejudice,</hi> the point that I have propounded, remains good upon thoſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> that I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged: But we ſhall need no other proofe of the point, then to produce ſome inſtances of <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54709:13"/>who have been rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompliſhed, and full of glorie. For the rule is, <hi>What is, may be.</hi> If ſome of the <hi>Sexe</hi> have been ſo, the Propoſition is firme, That the <hi>Sexe</hi> is capable, and <hi>may be ſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Some Inſtances of eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in Women.</hi> 1. <hi>Wiſdome. Policie. Deliberation. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſie.</hi> 2. <hi>Learning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat <hi>eminencie</hi> is thereto be named in men, which we have not diſcerned ſometimes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54709:13"/>to ſhine even in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Is it <hi>wiſdome, diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>policie?</hi> The wiſeſt of men hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, and ſpoken in their favour, in that proverb, <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.16. <hi>A gracious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man retaineth honour: and ſtrong men retaine riches.</hi> As mighty men by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and oppreſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come maſters of great wealth, ſo women that are meeke and gracious, by a more powerfull and ſurer claime, become the <hi>miſtreſſes</hi> of reputation, and have a prevailing and over-comming wiſdome,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54709:14"/>that entitles them, <hi>Ladies of Honour.</hi> It was the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter which the holy ghoſt hath given to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gail,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.3.</note> That ſhe was a woman of good underſtanding and of a beautifull countenance.</hi> And her ſtory all along, makes good the firſt part of that character. Her husband was a ſullen <hi>churliſh rich foole,</hi> and had poorely and unadviſedly thrown himſelfe into a quarrell with <hi>David,</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> at that time <hi>diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented,</hi> and in <hi>Armes.</hi> The Servants knowing <hi>Nabal</hi> to be incapable of found advice, for he was ſuch a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54709:14"/>ſon of Belial, that a man could not ſpeake to him; one of them therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints their <hi>Lady</hi> with the buſineſſe. She pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently apprehends the danger, and prevents it. She commands ſome of the family to attend her, and with a rich <hi>preſent</hi> in her hand, meets <hi>David</hi> now on the way towards <hi>Nabals</hi> houſe with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to deſtroy it. She knows ſo well how to frame her <hi>deportment</hi> and her <hi>language,</hi> that ſhe ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the <hi>inraged ſouldier,</hi> and overcomes him who never knew what it was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54709:15"/>to be overcome. If one would learne the ſkill of <hi>inſinuation,</hi> he need not learne any other <hi>poſture</hi> then hers, as ſoone as ſhe ſees <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.27, 24.</note> ſhe haſts, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to throw her ſelfe off from her ſaddle, then to alight, and falls on her face, and bowes her ſelfe to the ground before him, and falls at his feet. And what her behaviour had ſpoken, She ſpeakes over againe with ſuch words as might well have bin penned by one of the greateſt Maſters of policie and wit. And that <hi>Woman</hi> hath <hi>a name
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54709:15"/>of wiſedome,</hi> though we know her by no other <hi>name,</hi> who is mentioned in the hiſtorie of <hi>King Davids</hi> warres. The towne of <hi>Abel</hi> where this woman dwelt, had foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly taken part with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious <hi>Sheba,</hi> and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him that was the very head of the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. <hi>Joab</hi> the <hi>Kings Generall</hi> layes ſeige to the Towne, and was likely to take it by <hi>ſtorming. Then cryed this wiſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man out of the citie, Heare,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.16.</note> heare, ſay I pray you unto Ioab, come neere hither, that I may ſpeake with thee.</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54709:16"/>And having obtained a <hi>parlee,</hi> ſe how ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds and prevailes. <hi>I am one of them</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>that are peaceable and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Iſrael: Thou ſeekeſt to deſtroy a city and mother in Iſrael: Why wilt thou ſwallow up the Inheritance of the Lord?</hi> When the Generall had told her up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what termes he would raiſe the ſeige: She un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to perſuade with the Inhabitants, and doth ſo: for preſently they threw the head of <hi>Sheba</hi> the <hi>Rebell,</hi> over the wall, and the Generall is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed and retreats. <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:54709:16"/>hath given us a <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel</hi> to this, of the <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of the <hi>Celticke wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who when their Countrie was fallen, through miſ-underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and differences, into a Civill warre, would not reſt, or give over their <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation,</hi> till <hi>Armes</hi> were laid down, and peace was ſetled thorough all their Cities and Families, which was ſo great a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to their Countrie, and ſo acceptable, that it grew to a cuſtome among them, to call and admit their women to <hi>Councell.</hi> And in the league which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54709:17"/>long after they made with <hi>Hannibal,</hi> this was one <hi>Article,</hi> which for the ſtrangeneſſe and fame of it, I will record: <hi>If the Celtans have any matter of complaint againſt the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians, the Carthagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Commanders in Spain ſhall judge of it: But if the Carthaginians have any thing to object againſt the Celtans, it ſhall be brought before the Celtan women.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Policie</hi> of <hi>Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme</hi> is reckoned to the family of <hi>wiſdome.</hi> See what an Engine that great man <hi>Ioab</hi> uſed to bring about the <hi>Court Deſigne</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:54709:17"/>to have the popular young Prince <hi>Abſalom</hi> brought backe from his baniſhment.
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.</note> He ſubornes a woman of <hi>Tekoah,</hi> who needed not much inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but acts it with ſuch cloſeneſſe and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming paſſion, that <hi>David</hi> though a wiſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Prince, had much a-doe to find out the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and when he found it, yet ſhe ſo carried on the buſineſſe, even beyond her inſtructions, that ſhe fully brought about the mind of the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if either <hi>Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>Secrecie</hi> be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54709:18"/>to wiſdome, we find even theſe <hi>Qualities</hi> (which many think moſt unlikely to be found) in women. When <hi>Manoah</hi> was ſurpriſed, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough preſent conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion gave himſelfe for a dead and loſt man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had ſeen an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel;</hi> his wife recovers her ſelfe and him out of that diſtemper, and deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſons that with which her husband was confounded,
<note place="margin">Judg. 13.23.</note> 
                  <hi>If</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>the Lord were pleaſed to kill us, he would not have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a burnt offring and a meat offring at our hands,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54709:18"/>neither would he have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us all theſe things, nor would as at this time have told us ſuch things as theſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Secrecie,</hi> (of the want of which we do ordinarily accuſe them) behold the carriage of two women recorded in Scripture. <hi>Rahab,</hi> who not only hid <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> ſpies in her houſe,
<note place="margin">Joſh. 2.</note> but alſo locked up their great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe ſafely in her breſt: and though ſhe were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to communicate the thing to divers friends, ſhe doth manage it with ſo much privacie
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54709:19"/>and ſilence, that nothing was diſcovered, but ſhe and all her friends, were ſaved in the common ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie of her Country. That other is, that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Bahurim,</hi> who preſerved <hi>Ionathan</hi> and <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> whom <hi>David</hi> ſent to gather up intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And I might adde as a paralell, <hi>Epicharia</hi> in the <hi>Romane ſtory,</hi> from whoſe breſt, no threats nor tortures could force a ſecret that lay there concerning a conſpiracie againſt <hi>Nero.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Is it <hi>Learning</hi> that gives eminencie to men?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54709:19"/>In this alſo, <hi>women</hi> have a full ſhare. The <hi>Antients</hi> who delivered almoſt all things in <hi>Mythologies</hi> and <hi>Fables,</hi> intended this when they made <hi>Minerva</hi> an <hi>Inventreſse</hi> and <hi>Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi> of Learning, as well as <hi>Apollo</hi> the Inventor and Patron. And as for Inſtances, they are plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull under this head. In the Scripture, we have <hi>Huldah</hi> the <hi>Propheteſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ki. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4</note> who dwelt in the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> with whom thoſe prime <hi>Stateſ-men, Hilkiah, Ahikam, Achbor, Shaphan,</hi> and <hi>Aſahiah,</hi> thought it no diſparagement to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54709:20"/>And can we judge other of <hi>Priſcilla</hi> then that ſhe was learned, being able to inſtruct more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly that rare young man <hi>Apollos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 18.24 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>He zych. vor tit.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> a man elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, (or as <hi>Hezychias</hi> paraphraſeth it, <hi>A man learned in Hiſtorie,</hi>) and mightie in the Scripture? But beſides thoſe that have their names in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Record, other <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> both Eccleſiaſticall and Secular, antient and moderne, are plentifull in Examples. <hi>Aſpatia</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed <hi>Pericles,</hi> who of a great <hi>Souldier</hi> was one of the beſt <hi>Orators</hi> that hath
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54709:20"/>been bred in <hi>Greece. Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philia</hi> wrote many books of <hi>Hiſtorie,</hi> which when they were extant were much eſteemed. <hi>Cornelia</hi> the mother of the <hi>Gracchi</hi> was ſuch a Miſtreſſe of Eloquence, that <hi>Cicero</hi> admired ſome of her Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <hi>Athenais</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a meane father, was yet thought worthy to be the wife of one of the <hi>Chriſtian Emperours</hi> for her Wit and Learning. <hi>Eudoxia</hi> the <hi>Empreſse</hi> of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the <hi>younger,</hi> wrote learned <hi>Poëms,</hi> and eſpecially one very ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular one concerning our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54709:21"/>Saviour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> of <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaks very high things of his ſiſter <hi>Gorgonia.</hi> And ſo doth <hi>Hierome</hi> of divers excellent <hi>Romane Ladies.</hi> Neither have latter times wanted ſuch ornaments. <hi>Olympia Fulvia Morata,</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> by birth, not long after the <hi>Reformation</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the preaching of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> beſides her exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite knowledge in the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> and <hi>Greeke</hi> tongues, attained to the happineſſe of knowing <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and leaving her Countrie for Conſcience ſake, marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>Germanie,</hi> ſhe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54709:21"/>gave her ſelfe with much ſucceſſe to the ſtudie of the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi> Of our owne, among many others that might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, I will only name, The Lady <hi>Iane Gray</hi> (unhappy only in being forced for a while to weare a Crown) a <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> who beſide the <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Greeke,</hi> had this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage beyond <hi>Morata,</hi> that ſhe knew the <hi>Hebrew</hi> alſo, and was thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to ſatisfie her ſelfe in both the <hi>Originals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in ſtead of more examples in this kind, I will produce that great
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54709:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54709:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:54709:23"/>Ornament of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, Anna Maria van Schurman,</hi> pleading and diſputing the truth of what I have now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, with that <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> and <hi>Reverend Divine, Andreas Rivet,</hi> that from a <hi>Womans Pen,</hi> yee may have an <hi>Apologie</hi> for tho <hi>learned Pen's</hi> of <hi>Women.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Letters touching this argument between</hi> Andreas Rivet, <hi>and</hi> Anna Maria <hi>à</hi> Schurman.</head>
               <p>FOr the confirmation
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54709:23"/>of the point in hand, and for the honour of that <hi>Maiden Pen,</hi> I will tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late into our own tongue for the uſe of our Engliſh women, ſo much of that learned Letter as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes this preſent argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which that renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Virgin, <hi>Anne Marie Schurma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> of <hi>Vtrecht</hi> wrote in <hi>Latine,</hi> to the Reverend and famous French Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, <hi>Andrew Rivet,</hi> then at <hi>Leyden,</hi> which <hi>Doctor Beverwick</hi> a learned <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian</hi> of <hi>Dort</hi> hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated together with a <hi>Diſsertation</hi> upon the ſame ſubject by the ſame <hi>Lady.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:54709:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Rivet</hi> by a Letter dated from <hi>Leyden</hi> the <hi>Kalends</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1632. having received ſome <hi>French Verſes</hi> of <hi>Schurmans</hi> which he preſented to the <hi>Princeſse</hi> of Arts and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature, <hi>Princeſse Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> Siſter to the <hi>Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince Palatine,</hi> from whoſe learned judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they had received approbation, and having given the <hi>Noble Schurman</hi> her due praiſe, he lets fall theſe words, <hi>That her abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities were a prooſe to the preſent times and to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that if many women doe not the like, it is not out of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54709:24"/>defect of wit or judgement, but becauſe they will not apply their minds to them, or cannot by reaſon of other lower aſſaires; neither is it expedient that many ſhould chuſe this kind of life, only it is ſufficient if ſome called to it by a ſpeciall inſtinct, doe ſhine forth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon theſe laſt words ſhe takes hold, and in a Letter dated at <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> the eighth of the <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1638. after ſome other Salutations and Complements in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſhe thus writes:</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:54709:25"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <q>
                        <p>YOur letters hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore written unto mee, gave me occaſion to doubt what your opinion is in whole concerning this thing, in which after you have ſpoken many things lovingly and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (as you uſe to doe of mee and my ſtudies) thus you write: <hi>Neither haply may it be expedient that many chooſe this kind of life; it is ſufficient if ſome, called to it by a ſpeciall inſtinct, doe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhine forth.</hi> I eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſent, if here we
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54709:25"/>meane ſuch women as have the care of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, or others that are neceſſarily imployed that way; but I am hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawn to that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if it be meant of maid's indowed with wit, and of generous education, many of which this age of ours brings forth. The great admiration of Sciences or the equitie of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right, inforceth me that I cannot indure, that that which in the opinion of every one is moſt worthy, ſhould be rarely found in our Sex.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54709:26"/>For whereas wiſedome is ſo great an ornament of humane kind, ſo that by right it belongs to all and every one, (ſo farre as it agrees to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones condition,) I ſee not why this <hi>Attire,</hi> the moſt handſome of all others, ſhould not be fit for a Virgin, in whom we allow a care to dreſſe and adorne her ſelfe. Neither is there any cauſe why the <hi>State</hi> ſhould be jealous of this: for the glorie of the learned Order no way darkens the luſtre of Magiſtrates. Yea,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54709:26"/>contrarily, all agree in this, that that State muſt at length be moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, that ſhall have many ſubjects, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to wiſdome, as well as to the Lawes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, neither Vertue, nor the learned Ranke it ſelfe, ſhall have their due honour or dignitie, unleſſe the greater part of people be ſuch, as are able not only blindly to admire, but by a true eſtimation to diſcerne the honour and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of Learning. But leſt I ſtay too long in the Porch, I enter upon
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54709:27"/>the ſtate of the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, which being rightly laid, the whole truth will clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. The principall Queſtion therefore is, <hi>Whether the ſtudie of Learning and Arts, be fit for a Virgin, eſpecially in theſe times.</hi> They are no light Arguments that perſwade mee, to favour the Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part. For that I may begin with the <hi>Civill Law,</hi> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I once read in <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian,</hi> That women are not to meddle with ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill or publike offices.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54709:27"/>But with what equitie this law was made, I will not now much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, this at leaſt I thinke may be clearly proved from thence, that the leiſure in which we live is allowed and lawfull. For hence we have much freedome of time, and quietneſſe which is a friend to the <hi>Muſes,</hi> but chiefly when by a ſpeciall kind of Prerogative, we are not tyed up by neceſſarie occaſions, nor ingaged upon domeſticall cares and buſineſſes. But yet truely this large and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54709:28"/>emptie ſpace of life, where it is ſpent looſly and negligently, where it is not laid out upon ſomewhat that is good, it becomes an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie for all vices. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> notably, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, Idleneſſe is the fountain of miſchiefes. And that we may avoid this <hi>Charibdis,</hi> ſhall the mind by little and little grow ſoft, and turned into the ſimilitude of that idleneſſe and ſloth in which it lyes? What therefore is to be done? Behold, <hi>Seneca</hi> a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime teacher opens a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54709:28"/>way between the rocks. When (ſaith he) they only are at leiſure (that is, doe beſt injoy their leiſure) who are at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for wiſdome, they only live, for they doe not only looke to their owne time well, but make benefit of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ages. For we muſt not ſeeke leiſure from the worthieſt employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but improve our leiſure in them: ſo our calmer freedome in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacie, will make our time neither weariſome nor tedious unto us. For there are two
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54709:29"/>things, (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith) which make others dull, but ſharpen a wiſe man, namely leiſure and ſolitarineſſe. But ſome uſe to object, that it is a ſufficient ſtudie for wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to handle the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe and the Needle. I confeſſe many think ſo, and the inveterate ill opinion of our times is every where for them. But we walke not by this Lesbian Rule, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Reaſon, rather then to cuſtome. For by what right, I pray, are theſe things fallen to our lot? By a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54709:29"/>right, or Humane? They ſhall never prove, that thoſe limits are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fatall, or preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed from Heaven to us, by that to lay a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon us. For if we fetch witneſſe from Antiquitie, both the Examples of all ages, and alſo the authoritie of the greateſt men, will evince the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; as that moſt noble ornament of the <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces</hi> hath ſhewed no leſſe pleaſantly then learnedly in his little booke, which he hath entituled, <hi>The Equality
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54709:30"/>of men and women.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">L'egalite des homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; des femines.</note> But leſt, as they ſay, I doe what hath been done before, I forbeare theſe things: I ſhall content my ſelf plainly to ſhew, that greater matters do not only become us, but alſo in this manner of life are expected from us. For neither will more generous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations indure to be curbed within ſuch nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row bounds, nor will ſharpe and high wits ſuffer themſelves to be kept under alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their naturall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Truly, if theſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54709:30"/>ſevere Lawes ſhould be of force, I ſhould not much wonder at it, if ſome women ſhould ſometimes be carried away with the intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of pleaſures, out of their contempt of this low employment. Beſides, then we could have no hope left here, of any honour, any dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, any reward of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, by which ſuch ſoules as are not dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate are wont chiefly to be incouraged, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after things praiſe-worthy. In vain doe we boaſt our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54709:31"/>bilitie which we recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of our Anceſtors, if preſently a ſlothfull ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie doe cloud it. Hence it is, that he that reades Hiſtorie, ſhall often in the longeſt tract of time diſcerne no more the monuments of our Sexe, then the path of a Ship paſſing thorow the Sea. But, they will ſay, Whence ſhould you have glory? Whence immortall fame? Doe ye expect it from your leaſure? Why not? But I meane from leaſure brightned with the light of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54709:31"/>For it becomes us to grow famous under the preſidencie, not ſo much of the Armed, as the gowned <hi>Pallas.</hi> Moreover, where true Phyloſophie hath ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her ſelfe in the Throne of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, no doore will ever ſtand open to the vain or wandring mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of an unconſtant mind: which alſo <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> the notable Patron of all polite Learning hath obſerved expreſly, where he ſpeaketh of the Education of Sir <hi>Thomas More's</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54709:32"/>in theſe words: <hi>Nothing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth ſo wholly fill the breaſt of a Damoſell, as ſtudie.</hi> For how ſhall we not eaſily ſcorn the <hi>Pagean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie</hi> of this world, the ſpecious authoritie of examples, and the poore vanities of the times, when from the high turret of wiſdome we look down upon theſe earthly things. Further, whereas it is no leſſe the dutie, then the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of all, to ſtrive after the perfection of our primitive Originall, (from which there is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54709:32"/>none of us but have fallen) we muſt labour, that his Image, who is the Light &amp; the Truth, may begin more and more to ſhine in the higheſt pallace of our mind. And although I deny not here, that <hi>Theologie</hi> (which is that which chiefly perfects the underſtanding) doth all; yet I know not how, but me thinkes they ſeeme not enough to obſerve the Majeſtie of ſo great a Queen, who would have her goe abroad alone and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attended. For when we
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54709:33"/>look into the volumne of naturall things, who ſees not how the parts of both theſe Sciences do agree among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a beautifull harmonie? How much help, how much light, the one brings to the other? Nor ought this much to trouble us, that ſome ſhut up this ſtudie into ſo narrow a roome, thinking it doth not much concern us, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this frame of the world grew together of moat's? Whether it ſtruggled forth out of a rude Chaos? Whether
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54709:33"/>ſome <hi>Bodies</hi> enjoy an heavenly nature, others a terrene? Whether the upper frame of the world be whirled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and whether they be not giddy, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that not the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, but the earth turns round? Whether the Sun ſetting be plunged into the Ocean? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Antipodes alſo have its light? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Earth be of a ſquare figure or round? Finally, Whether the Horizon terminate the whole world, or only our ſight? If that which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54709:34"/>is vulgarly ſpoken to our reproach were to be heeded, they would make us to fruſtrate God the Creator of all his end, who brought us into this Theatre to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, know, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workes. For nature was not ſuch a Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame unto us, that ſhe would forbid us the ſight of her: elſe, why would ſhe beſtow that upon us, which the Philoſopher affirmes is planted in all men, namely, The deſire of knowing? Why would
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54709:34"/>ſhe give us an erect Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, unleſſe we ſhould lift up our eyes and our mindes alſo, unto the contemplation of her ſelfe? We ſhould be Stocks, and not of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane kind; Strangers, not inhabitants of this world, if we could not bring our mind raiſed, and as it were inſlamed with divine love, to ſo beautifull, ſo glorious things, in which the Majeſtie of the eternall God-head ſhines forth. Neither may we think that we have done our duty, if we only ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54709:35"/>looke at theſe things as it were in our paſſing by. For ſo we ſee them, not that we may know them, for hereby we ſhew that we do not ſee, what we have no deſire to know further. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing under our eye, more admirable then man, nothing more beautifull then the dwelling place of the Soul: but how little is that which is judged of only by the skinne, or the outward forme? How miſerably may we bluſh at thoſe ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54709:35"/>Hymnes of Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks, in which, while they curiouſly pry into Nature, and by prying approach neerer to the firſt cauſe of all things, even they every where are wont to ſing forth the praiſes of the high Workman. Further, as oft as we apply our ſelves to follow that bright Starre of holy Scripture, who will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but we may be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by ſo many Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of holy men, who from hence have taken occaſion to praiſe their God, to the returne of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54709:36"/>the ſame thankfulneſſe?</p>
                        <p>But, not to ſay any thing now in generall of the ſtudy of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which now adayes is almoſt only follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Nurſeries, and in the Courts of great men, only by the way we will inquire, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the knowledge of Publike Affaires may befit every private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? I ſhould eaſily grant indeed, that it conferres directly to practiſe, and the uſe of the Republike: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Theorie, and the peculiar fruits
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54709:36"/>which thence redound to every one, we think none are to neglect it. The holy Scriptures go before us here, and not only goe before us, but leade us by the hand. There the Orders of times are knit together by the Periods of the Monarchies; There both the Originals, and decayes of greateſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are either deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or foretold; and it is no wonder, ſeeing the marvellous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, which it is fit we ſhould duly obſerve, appeare in a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54709:37"/>more eminent matter, and ſeeing theſe uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſals cannot fall out within the age of one man, if God would have this ſtudie to be laid to heart by all. Shall not the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of this admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Government ſtrike up our harpes alſo; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Kingly Pſalmiſt wholly faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his mind, never leaves crying out; <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>How great are thy works, O Lord, thy thoughts are very deep?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:54709:37"/>
                     <p>
                        <q>It may be ſome will here object, This is no other then to commend a monaſticke life, or to make ſpeculation only our whole dutie. But ſo reaſon ſeems to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that firſt we ſhould looke at our ſelves, for ſo much as concernes our own hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; and then to our neighbour. For in vaine ſhall he have leiſure to attend upon others, who was never yet rightly at leaſure for himſelfe. In vaine doth he indeavour to help others by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell or fact,</q> who cannot
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54709:38"/>helpe himſelfe. In vaine ſhall he pretend to civil converſation, or to the bond of that more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime adminiſtration of Chriſtians, that is a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at home. I pray, what raſhnes would it be, to thinke to build that whole aeconomie of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall virtues, upon igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or the vulgar o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions: Yea for the moſt part unles by ſome chance the examples of all ages doe ſhew, that no one did ever happily ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to ſo great Dieties, unles he came furniſhed with great and ſolid lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:54709:38"/>For that is it which prepares, diſpoſeth, and makes us fitt to doe well, and lifts up our minds to the attempts of famous exploit's.</p>
                     <p>Againe nothing is more profitable for a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, nothing more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, then to diſcerne what is filthy and what is honeſt, what hurtfull and what harmeles, what is fitting and what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comelie. But how much knowledge of things, how great a dexteritie of judging doth that ſtand in need of? Seeing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this ſort of prudence
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54709:39"/>may not be learned of our ſelves, neither were it ſafe, we muſt therfore have recourſe to hiſtorie, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to dreſſe as it were by the glaſſe framing the life after the virtues of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Wee, I ſay, who when any blemiſh is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, though but by a wrong ſuſpition, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be reconciled againe to reputation: therefore maidens ought to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, not only to decline evill after they have ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed upon us, but alſo ſpecially to prevent them
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:54709:39"/>leſt they doe ſo.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, that I may now in ſilence paſſe by, the Arts and Sciences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall (as they call them,) which being prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals doe neceſſarilie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Queen as hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayds, I cannot but I muſt needs touch in a word how much wee ought to delight in many tongues, cheifely if they be attained for uſe, not for oſtentation. For Tongues are the faithfull keepers, yea the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of thoſe things which wiſe Antiquity hath left unto us: which
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54709:40"/>where it ſpeakes to us in its owne Idiome, it leaves in our mind a genuine i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of it ſelfe, and with a certain marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous grace and pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe affects our ſence, which we not without reaſon complaine is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in all tranſlations, yea though the very beſt. But if I would diſcourſe to you, how pleaſant it is, and how fruitfull, to draw forth, explicate, and prove heavenly doctrine from the very fountaines, it were no other then what is ſaid in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54709:40"/>To lend light to the Sunne.</p>
                     <p>But that I may make an end, I will here produce one example, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes is in my thoughts. One example I ſay, of the Incomparable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, <hi>Iane Gray,</hi> to whom no nation, no age (let me ſpeake it with the good leave of all) will yeild her equall. <hi>Michael Angel</hi> a <hi>Florentine</hi> who fully and pathetically deſcribes the hiſtory of her life &amp; death, in that conference which ſhe had with <hi>Fecknam</hi> the meſſenger of her appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching death, hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54709:41"/>theſe things among others: that ſhe deſpiſing thoſe gifts, (which yet were rare ones that God had given her,) and her nobility of blood, and beautie of her ſhape, and flouriſhing youth, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe might have procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red glory and favour to her ſelfe in this world; She pronounced with great courage, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ſo acceptable to her in her whole life, as that ſhe had the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the three learned tongues as they cal them. Now if the pleaſure or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, which we may
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54709:41"/>have from that in this life, may come under the name of true felicitie, ſhe confeſſed ſhe had it in the ſtudie of good letters, and ſpecially of the holy Scriptures. And though many doe greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe theſe ſtudies in a woman, yet ſhe her ſelfe becauſe of the great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of mind, which ſhe had thence received, and ſtill felt within her, did account their opinion to be unreaſonable. Behold Swanlike notes, brought forth, not under the ſhade of ſchooles, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the laſt act of a moſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54709:42"/>glorious Martyrdome, which I pray who would not reverence as an ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. Theſe things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning no light matters, I have not doubted to prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle unto you, being confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the indulgence of your fatherly love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mee. But I breake off, leſt I might ſeeme wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſay all that could be ſaid, or that I were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unmindfull of your affaires. Farewell, father, deare to me in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpects, &amp; vouchſafe in my name to ſalute your beloved wife,
<q>
                           <hi>Vtrecht</hi> 8. <hi>Id. of</hi> Wholly at your comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, <hi>March</hi> 1638. <hi>Anna Maria a Schurman.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:54709:42"/>
                     <p>I have thought fit to doe this honour to this <hi>Honourable</hi> and <hi>Learned Maid,</hi> as to tranſlate and tranſcribe ſo much of hers touching the <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> in hand. I have taken the libertie, though preciſely to obſerve her <hi>Conceits,</hi> yet to varie the <hi>Elegancies</hi> of her <hi>Latine Stile,</hi> into ſuch a <hi>Phraſe</hi> as is moſt <hi>naturall</hi> to our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and I hope with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any wrong to her, whom I much honour for her <hi>Pen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:54709:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Other Inſtances of womens eminencies.</hi> 3. <hi>Conſtancie.</hi> 4. <hi>Courage.</hi> 5. <hi>Abilitie to govern.</hi> 6. <hi>Piety and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat I may purſue this point a little, I will take notice of a few other particulars.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Constancie</hi> and <hi>Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> is accounted a <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> vertue; and it is charged upon the other whole <hi>Sexe</hi> that they are <hi>inconſtant</hi> and <hi>mutable.</hi> The Emperours <hi>Diocleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>Maximinian</hi> in a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:54709:43"/>publike <hi>Instrument</hi> call Womens wils <hi>Momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</hi> But to the contrarie, how famous was <hi>Ruth</hi> even for her <hi>Constancie,</hi> who notwithſtanding all aſſaults againſt it, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that nothing but death ſhould ſeparate her from her husbands mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?
<note place="margin">Ruth 1.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Intreat me not</hi> (ſaid ſhe to <hi>Naomi</hi>) <hi>to leave thee, or to returne from fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after thee; for whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goeſt, I will goe; and where thou lodgeſt, I will lodge; thy people ſhall be my people, and thy God my God: where thou dyeſt, will I die, and there will I be
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54709:44"/>buried; the Lord do ſo to me and more alſo, if ought but death part thee and me.</hi> She was not as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of his ſonne <hi>Reuben,
<note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.4</note> Vnſtable as water,</hi> and therefore he could not excell; but ſhe <hi>ſtrengthened her ſelfe,</hi> as the Originall Phraſe is, or as our <hi>Interpreters</hi> have rendred the Text, She was <hi>ſtedfaſtly minded.</hi> And if I ſhould mention the conſtant Reſolution of many <hi>women-martyrs,</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Perſecutions,</hi> or only of that time of tryall that was here in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, I ſhould eaſily make up a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54709:44"/>full hiſtorie. Yea, Queen <hi>Maries</hi> own ſiſter, as ſhe was an Example of her crueltie, ſo ſhe was a rare <hi>Pattern</hi> of this vertue, who as her word was, <hi>Semper eadem,</hi> She an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered it to the full in her courſe of life, as Sir <hi>Robert Nanton</hi> takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it in his <hi>Preface</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of <hi>Cambdens Elizabeth,</hi> where he compares her with, and much preferres her to K. <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> for this very grace.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas <hi>Valour</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> have been almoſt appropriated to man. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:54709:45"/>are not wanting in the mention of even an <hi>Heroicall Courage</hi> in ſome women. <hi>Jael</hi> the wife of <hi>Heber</hi> had the honour to rid away a great tyrant from the earth;
<note place="margin">Judg. 4.21</note> ſo that both the warre was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by her name, <hi>In the dayes of Iael</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>the high wayes were unoccupted,
<note place="margin">Judg. 5.6.</note> and the travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers walked thorough by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</hi> And <hi>Deborah</hi> ſings the renowne of her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit:
<note place="margin">Judg 5.24, 25, 26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed above women ſhall Iael the wife of Heber the Kenite be, bleſſed ſhall ſhe be above women in the Tent: he asked water, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:54709:45"/>ſhe gave him milke, ſhe brought forth butter in a lordly diſh: ſhe put her hand to the nayle, and her right hand to the workmans ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: and with the hammer ſhe ſmote Siſera, ſhe ſmote off his head, when ſhe had pierced &amp; ſtricken through his Temple. At her feet he bowed, he fell, he lay down, at her feet he bowed, he fell where he bowed, there he fell downe dead.</hi> An <hi>Heroicke</hi> act, ſet out in an Heroick ſtraine. And that woman of <hi>Thebez,</hi> mentioned alſo in the Hiſtorie of the <hi>Iudges,</hi> ſeemes to have been more valiant, and to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54709:46"/>have ventured more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly then the men that were incloſed with her in the <hi>Tower,</hi> who when nothing but threats and flames were before her, had the courage to caſt a piece of a milſtone upon <hi>Abimelech's</hi> head.
<note place="margin">Judg. 9.53</note> But I moſt admire Queen <hi>Heſther,</hi> who forgetting her ſoftneſſe and delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, reſolved to ſerve her people, though her ſelfe ſhould periſh in the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. <hi>I will goe in unto the King,</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>which is not according to the law, and if I periſh, I periſh.</hi> Out of other Stories, I will
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54709:46"/>adde but one. When the <hi>Melians</hi> under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of young <hi>Nymphaeus</hi> to disburthen their own Countrey too full of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, ſeeking an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation elſewhere, were for a while entertained by the <hi>Carians,</hi> they had been likely to have found their tombs there by a treacherie, which was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered under the faire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of an Invitation to a banquet. The <hi>Melians</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome intelligence of the plot, returning anſwer that their cuſtome was never to feaſt without the companie of their wives,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54709:47"/>they accordingly come themſelves <hi>unarmed,</hi> (to avoid ſuſpition,) but all their <hi>women</hi> with <hi>ſwords</hi> hid under their Gownes, (to provide for their ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.) About the middle of the feaſt, the word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given by the <hi>Carians,</hi> they indeavoured to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their treacherie, but inſtantly every one of the <hi>Melian</hi> women delivers her ſword to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, whereby they bravely acquitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and afterwards had leaſure to admire the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedneſſe of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who undiſturbed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54709:47"/>through weakneſs or fear, were <hi>Actors</hi> as well as <hi>Spectators</hi> of that exploit. It would be too much to produce the many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of their generous actions, whether for the preſervation of their Countries, or for the love of their husbands, or for the maintainance of the Religion of their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors. It appeares then, that men have no reaſon to challenge <hi>Courage,</hi> as if it were alone tyed to their <hi>Sexe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. There is yet another vertue whereof men doe boaſt, which is, The <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54709:48"/>to govern,</hi> and to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage Publike Affaires.</hi> Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine-Rule</hi> hath not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had <hi>enemies</hi> of late, but even the <hi>antient Times</hi> and <hi>Lawes</hi> have been but too injurious to them. The <hi>Parthians</hi> and <hi>Thracians</hi> while they remained <hi>Barbarous,</hi> uſed their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as <hi>Slaves.</hi> And the <hi>old Nations</hi> that were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Civill,</hi> dealt with them little better. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Achaians</hi> gave them the libertie of <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> therefore <hi>Homer</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfully uſed to call them in his verſes, not
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54709:48"/>
                  <hi>Achaians</hi> but <hi>Achaides.</hi> And it fell from the Pen of the wiſe <hi>Plutarch,</hi> That it is <hi>a Praevarication of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to be governed of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> The <hi>Athenians</hi> ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, how farre they ſhould meddle. And the <hi>Romane Lawes</hi> appointed Tutors and Curators, not only in unripe yeares, but even in <hi>widow-hood.</hi> But all this prejudice againſt them among <hi>Heathen Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> perhaps would not be much weighed; if there were not ſome that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the <hi>Scripture</hi> to ſay the ſame thing: for there are that urge that of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54709:49"/>Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 3.12.</note> As for my people, children are their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsours, and women rule over them.</hi> We grant, that many times women were great <hi>miſchiefes</hi> to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> as we ſee in the times of <hi>Iezabel, Maacah,</hi> and <hi>Athaliah:</hi> But it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be that the Spirit of God doth ſimply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſeeing it hath given teſtimony concerning <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah,</hi> that ſhe was ſo able for publike management, that the Text ſaith,
<note place="margin">Judg. 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>She judged Iſrael,</hi> and, <hi>The children of Iſrael came up to her for judgement.</hi> I might
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54709:49"/>give <hi>Pulcheria</hi> as a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel, famous in the <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Hiſtorians,</hi> who preſerved the Empire while her brother lived, and after his death gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it with great <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> calling <hi>Marcian</hi> to her aſſiſtance. But we that are of the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> need no proofe of this, whileſt the memory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines of that <hi>Queen of her Subjects hearts,</hi> I mean, and every bodie knowes I meane <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> of whom we have the <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie</hi> of an <hi>enemie,</hi> even Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> who though plotting againſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54709:50"/>her life, yet admired her, and was wont to ſay, that <hi>Elizabeth of England, and Henry the fourth of France, were able to rule the whole world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Hitherto, in all the particulars mentioned, men have <hi>boaſted,</hi> but there is one, the maine, in which they have ſcarce ſo much as pretended to <hi>outſtrip</hi> them; and that is the <hi>higheſt improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> namely <hi>pietie</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> unto which they have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what the greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in regard that their <hi>Affections</hi> are ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54709:50"/>more lively and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. As Chriſt ſpake, the text tells us,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uk. 11.17.</note> 
                  <hi>a certain woman of the company lift up her voice, and ſaid unto him, Bleſsed is the wombe that bare thee, and the paps which thou haſt ſucked.</hi> As he was led to be crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the women wept. And when he was nayled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, there were three <hi>Mary's</hi> and but one <hi>Iohn</hi> at the foote of it. But my buſineſſe is not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre them before men, but only to give them their due value; that if we reade grace and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the lives of men,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54709:51"/>wee may alſo take notice of holy and devout wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as the Scripture in divers places calls them, The <hi>Sarahs</hi> who were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, the <hi>Maries</hi> who were humble and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, the <hi>Elizabeths</hi> who walked in all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God blameles, the <hi>Dorcaſses</hi> who were fruitfull in workes of charitie and love, The <hi>Priſcilla's</hi> who were heavenly and rich in diſcourſe, The <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba's,</hi> the <hi>Lois's,</hi> and <hi>Eunice's</hi> who were care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in inſtructing their children in the knowledg
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54709:51"/>of God, and in a word, the <hi>Lydia's</hi> whoſe hearts God hath opened.</p>
               <p>I have a multitude of examples in my view, but I will not name ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. When the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> often paſſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough <hi>Shunem, A great woman</hi> there not only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained him, but moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to her husband the continuance, <hi>Behold now</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>I perceive that this is an holy man of God,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> King. 4.9, 10.</note> let us make a little cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I pray thee, on the wall, and let us ſet for him there a bed, and a table and a stoole, and a candleſtick.</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:54709:52"/>She was not only in her owne ſoule affected, but is an inſtrument to work upon her husband. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tels us, that there may be ſuch ſweetneſſe and holineſſe of converſation,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.1, 2</note> that men who obey not the word, may be won by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of their wives, while they behold their chaſte converſation joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with feare. I obſerve alſo concerning the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> of <hi>Shunem,</hi> whom I named, that ſhe never o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the times and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of <hi>Divine
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54709:52"/>worſhip;</hi> that ſpeech of her husbands to her, when ſhe deſired to goe to the Prophet,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King. 4.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Wherfore wilt thou goe to day? It is neither new moone nor Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath:</hi> Implies, that ſhe never uſed to omit thoſe publike dayes. And like to this, it ſeemes to me that in <hi>Pauls</hi> time, the women were more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in prayer then men in the citie of <hi>Philippi;
<note place="margin">Act. 16.13.</note> On the Sabbath (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Luke) we went out of the citie by a river ſide, where prayer was wont to be made and we ſate downe, and ſpake unto the women which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:54709:53"/>thither.</hi> Yea their ſerviceableneſſe in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not to be omitted, <hi>St Paul</hi> ſpeakes of women which <hi>laboured with him in the Goſpell.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.3.</note> And what might not be ſaid of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular graces, it might be eaſy to produce many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances out of Scripture, and to fit them with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hiſtories; but I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, as intending chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to ſpeake to the next point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:54709:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Soule glory is chiefest. What Soule glory or Inward beautie is.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I have more briefely paſſed thorough the firſt point, which though it be <hi>true,</hi> and the Truth of it neceſſarie to be knowne, yet may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by ſome weake ſpirits to <hi>Selfe-ſlatterie.</hi> It is a <hi>glaſse</hi> into which if ſome doe looke, it may be they may be proud. But the other <hi>glaſse</hi> that I am now to hold forth, I would invite All to look into, <hi>and often,</hi> for I hope
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:54709:54"/>it will not be without profit. The point as I propounded it in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, is</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>That the higheſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, is that of the Soul, and the greateſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of women is Soul-glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was an <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall glorie</hi> that did commend the <hi>daughter</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the expreſſion of that holy man, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he was, in <hi>King Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Court, who at the time of the <hi>marriage cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration,</hi> compoſed a <hi>ſong</hi> which he fitted upon <hi>Shoſhannim,</hi> thoſe <hi>ſix-ſtringed
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:54709:54"/>instruments</hi> of muſick, which <hi>David</hi> the late King had brought into the <hi>Quire,</hi> and raiſed his heart to the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the ſweet and heavenly Myſterie of the Union betwixt our Lord <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> and his <hi>Church.</hi> This was his maine deſigne, but his ground-worke, was the <hi>Praiſes</hi> of that incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Payre, King <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter, and he hath ſet forth thoſe Praiſes with ſuch <hi>High,</hi> and yet apt Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe, (who ere he
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54709:55"/>were) a maſter in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie. And no doubt both the <hi>Subjects</hi> of his <hi>Pen,</hi> were very praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, as for <hi>Solomon</hi> we know who he was; and the <hi>Lady</hi> though the daughter of a ſtranger, yet moſt probably was a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyte,</hi> and not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from <hi>Gentiliſme</hi> to the true Profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion then, but ſubdued powerfully and effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to grace and holineſſe, which ſeemes to be the reaſon of that expreſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13. <hi>The Kings daughter is all glorious within.</hi> I know there are
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54709:55"/>ſome that doe thus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete it, That ſhe was not only dreſt in <hi>Gold</hi> of <hi>Ophir,</hi> and in <hi>rayment of Needle-worke,</hi> when ſhe ſhewed her ſelfe abroad, and appeared in the eye of <hi>Solomons</hi> people, but alſo was richly clothed with <hi>wrought gold,</hi> when ſhe ſate within the houſe, to entertain the <hi>King.</hi> But I am moſt inclined to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive another interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That as ſhe had a goodly and beautifull preſence, ſo ſhe had a <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> and a <hi>fairer ſoul,</hi> becauſe I ſuppoſe <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> wiſe choyce, would
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:54709:56"/>be of an <hi>excellent woman.</hi> A <hi>Princeſse</hi> no doubt of all <hi>inward accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> of which her Sexe was capable. It is not then ſo much a <hi>comely feature,</hi> or a <hi>gracefull deportment,</hi> as the <hi>Qualification</hi> of the <hi>mind,</hi> a right <hi>frame</hi> of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> Without this, <hi>beautie</hi> it ſelfe is <hi>uncomely,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the ſame <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 11.22. <hi>As a Iewell of gold (Nezem,</hi> the Hebrew word is uſed both for an <hi>eare-ring,</hi> and <hi>Noſe-Iewell,</hi> it is the ſame word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.21. The <hi>Noſe-Iewell</hi> in uſe among the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> women, was tyed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:54709:56"/>with a ſtring upon the forehead, and ſo hung downe to the Noſe:) <hi>As a Iewell of gold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in a ſwines ſnout, ſo is a faire woman, which is without diſcretion.</hi> The ſenſe of the <hi>Proverbe</hi> is plaine: As it were a very ridiculous object to behold a dirtie <hi>Swine,</hi> with <hi>Diamonds</hi> or <hi>Pearles</hi> dangling at the eares, and a <hi>Pendant</hi> or <hi>Noſe-Iewell</hi> hanging on the brow, tumbling it ſelf into the next <hi>puddle,</hi> or rooting in a filthy ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming dunghill; even ſuch a ſight, and altogether as uncomely, is a woman
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:54709:57"/>of a pleaſant ſhape, but otherwiſe ignorant, rude, and wanton. And as for <hi>Ornaments,</hi> they doe not adde any value to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor can they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend one to God, for heare what the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, ſpeaking unto wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men chaſte and holy, <hi>Your adorning,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.3, 4.</note> let it not be that outward, of plaiting the haire, and of wearing of gold, or of putting on of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell; but let it be the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:54709:57"/>price.</hi> The <hi>painted Iezabel</hi> was a <hi>wretched woman,</hi> as King <hi>Iehu</hi> cals her,
<note place="margin">2 Ki. 9.30</note> though ſhe were a <hi>Kings daughter.</hi> She was <hi>vile</hi> in Gods eyes, and in mans. She thought her ſelfe <hi>fine,</hi> when ſhe had painted her ſelf, and look'd out at the window, but was indeed <hi>loathſome,</hi> as wanting this <hi>Soul-glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us then enquire, what <hi>Soul-glory,</hi> or <hi>inward</hi> beautie is.</p>
               <p>Every ſon and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Adam,</hi> are naturally <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>filthy.</hi> We were all <hi>polluted in our bloud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.6</note> and might juſtly have
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54709:58"/>been caſt out <hi>to the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our perſons in the day that we were borne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> King <hi>David</hi> acknowledges this and therefore cryes out for waſhing, purging, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Our parents were infected with <hi>Leproſie,</hi> and we are their uncleane iſſue;
<note place="margin">Job 14.4.</note> for, <hi>Who can bring a cleane thing out of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi> And his friend <hi>Eliphaz</hi> notably confirmes it,
<note place="margin">Job 15.14, 15, 16.</note> 
                  <hi>What is man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he ſhould be cleane? and he which is borne of a woman, that he ſhould be righteous? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the heavens are not cleane in Gods ſight: How
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54709:58"/>much more abominable and filthy is man, which drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth iniquitie like water?</hi> Where is then the <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die?</hi> or how come any to be <hi>cleane?</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath opened this <hi>Myſterie,</hi> writing to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> where he ſpeakes of thoſe that lye in their ſinnes,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>And ſuch</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but ye are juſtified in the Name of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a double cleanneſſe. 1. A waſhing from the guilt of ſinne;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54709:59"/>This is to be <hi>Iuſtifyed in the name of the Lord Ieſus,</hi> who is that <hi>fountaine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ſinne and for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſse,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Zacherie</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1. where he uſeth two words to import both <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall</hi> and <hi>original</hi> guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the one is <hi>hhattaath,</hi> Sinne, the other is, <hi>Nid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> ſeperation for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe, alluding to the time of the womans <hi>Seperation</hi> upon the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging forth of any child. This was the <hi>Deſigne</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> comming into the world, and giving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for the Church, <hi>that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54709:59"/>he might cleanſe it,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.26, 27.</note> and preſent it to himſelfe a glorious Church, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy, and without blemiſh.</hi> And thus being <hi>justifyed</hi> by <hi>Chriſts</hi> taking our guilt upon him,
<note place="margin">1 Ioh, 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>by his blood we are cleanſed from all ſinne,</hi> ſtanding cleare and acquitted at the <hi>Tribunal</hi> (as if we had never been uncleane by guilt) fully and perfectly. But, 2. There is a waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo from the <hi>pollution</hi> and <hi>filth</hi> of ſinne, being <hi>ſanctifyed by the Spirit of our God.</hi> And this is it
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54709:60"/>that I am now principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon. This is the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the whole man,</hi> or according to S <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſſion, <hi>A learning of Chriſt;</hi> which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards particularly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.20, 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>The putting off, concerning the former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, the old man which is corrupt, according to the deceitfull luſts,</hi> and <hi>a being renewed in the ſpirit of the mind, a putting on of the new man, which after God is created in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse and true holines.</hi> This is the proper worke of Gods holy and Sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Spirit,</hi> given unto all,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54709:60"/>to whom the Sonne is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this <hi>Spirit</hi> are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and very various, I will not now diſcourſe of all, but only of the <hi>graces of converſation,</hi> nor of all of them, for it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a large and diligent <hi>Treating.</hi> And therefore, whereas I might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend many <hi>Iewells</hi> fit for their <hi>luſtre</hi> to deck out an holy Soul, I ſhall only for the preſent make up one <hi>Iewel,</hi> of foure precious <hi>Iemm's,</hi> fit to be ſet upon the breaſt, or rather into the heart of a <hi>Princeſse</hi> or greateſt <hi>Lady</hi> or other <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:54709:61"/>where only the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> the moſt ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workeman can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it.</p>
               <p>The foure <hi>Graces of Converſation</hi> which I am commending are theſe;
<list>
                     <item>1. Modeſtie.</item>
                     <item>2. Humilitie.</item>
                     <item>3. Diſcretion.</item>
                     <item>4. Pietie.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Modeſtie proper to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Modeſtie of cariage. Of language. A cenſure of lewd bookes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>MOdestie.</hi> This is one of the moſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:54709:61"/>naturall and moſt uſefull <hi>Tables</hi> of the mind, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one may preſently reade, what is printed in the whole <hi>volume.</hi> It is as proper in the opinion of ſome, to the womans Sexe, as <hi>flying</hi> to a <hi>bird, ſwimming</hi> to a <hi>fiſh, beautie</hi> to a <hi>flower.</hi> Certainely a good heart lookes out thorough <hi>modeſt eyes,</hi> and gives an anſwer to any that aſkes, <hi>who is within?</hi> with <hi>modeſt words;</hi> and dwels not at the ſigne of the <hi>buſh</hi> or <hi>red lattice,</hi> or <hi>painted poſt.</hi> A glorious ſoule is above <hi>dreſses,</hi> and deſpiſeth ſuch as have no
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:54709:62"/>higher, or other thoughts, then what concerne their <hi>gorget</hi> and their <hi>hayre.</hi> The <hi>calme-conſtant-watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full-modeſt-compoſed-diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> is ſurely the moſt excellent temper, and the moſt uſefull, for this go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes the heart, and makes one fit and able to entertain thoſe pleaſures, by which others are loſt and undone. Such an one may pledge even <hi>Circe</hi> in her <hi>cup,</hi> and yet not be <hi>tranſformed:</hi> for ſuch an one will only <hi>ſlip,</hi> but not drinke deep of pleaſures lawfull. This preſerves in tune, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:54709:62"/>keeps the <hi>ſcale of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> even. This teaches a <hi>denying</hi> and <hi>preventing</hi> behaviour towards ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. 'Tis much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the <hi>Philoſophers wooll,</hi> to ſtop the <hi>car</hi> with. It is the beſt <hi>guardian</hi> both of the eye and eare. But let me deſcend to particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let the cariage and behaviour be modeſt.
<note place="margin">Gen. 24, 64.</note> 
                  <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bekah</hi> put on the <hi>vaile,</hi> when <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant told her, that the man whom they ſaw com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming towards them, was his <hi>maſters</hi> ſon, to whom ſhe was intended in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:54709:63"/>Contrarily, the woman with the attire of an harlot of whom <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſpeakes,
<note place="margin">Pro. 7.13.</note> 
                  <hi>met a young man and kiſſed him, and with an impudent face ſhe ſpake unto him.</hi> She was <hi>A confident</hi> as we may ſay, in the known ſence of that word; for whereas all wiſe and good men, have accounted <hi>bluſhing,</hi> to be the <hi>Table of virtue</hi> in women, She (as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall Text expreſſeth it) did <hi>ſtrengthen her face,</hi> as if ſhe reſolved to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the <hi>bluſh,</hi> and to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away the <hi>colour</hi> of <hi>ſhame.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:54709:63"/>
               <p>I profeſſe againſt <hi>court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and I know that I know little of <hi>Behaviour,</hi> yet this I know that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth call the modeſt behaviour, <hi>neate:</hi> for ſo the original word ſignifies, in that place,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. implying that ſuch a one who is modeſt, is of a <hi>cleane</hi> or <hi>neate</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour. <hi>Princeſses</hi> and <hi>great women</hi> have their <hi>teachers</hi> of behaviour; This is not the worke of <hi>Preachers,</hi> only where the <hi>Scripture</hi> is before us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Behaviour,</hi> wee may commend it, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect it; and according to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:54709:64"/>the Scriptures by which all muſt be Judged, wee ſay, That the <hi>moſt modeſt,</hi> is the <hi>most neate,</hi> and <hi>moſt-becomming</hi> cariage. Then, what are they that <hi>ſpeake with their feet,</hi> as <hi>Solomons</hi> phraſe is, or according to the character, that the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> gives them, <hi>That walke with ſtretched ſorth necks,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.16.</note> and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as they goe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a thinkling with their feet.</hi> How would that <hi>Court-prophet</hi> (for ſo he was) have deſcribed ſome <hi>ſtrange creatures</hi> that we ſometimes ſee, practiſing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:54709:64"/>the <hi>affected Shrug,</hi> and acting, or the <hi>ſtrutting,</hi> or the <hi>dancing,</hi> or the <hi>ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> or the <hi>ſwimming</hi> poſture; with what ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe, with what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, would he have ſpoken againſt theſe wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons? But I forbeare en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement in this matter, as having no delight to be long in the company of ſuch light and childiſh ſpirits, <hi>objects</hi> at which wiſe men laugh, and good men mourne.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let the language be modeſt. That rule of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> concernes both men and women, though
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:54709:65"/>now I in ſpeciall apply it unto women, <hi>Let no corrupt communication pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of your mouth,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.29</note> but that which is good to the uſe of edifying, that it may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister grace unto the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and grieve not the holy Spirit of God.</hi> Unſavorie and prophane ſpeech grieves the holy Ghoſt, and holy men; and is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unbefitting thoſe that profeſſe Godlineſſe: for ſo the ſame <hi>Apostle</hi> in the next Chapter; <hi>As for uncleanneſſe let it not be once named among you,
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.3, 4</note> as becommeth Saints, neither filthineſse, nor fooliſh tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:54709:65"/>nor jeſting, which are not convenient.</hi> Ye ſhall obſerve in the reading of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Pen-men</hi> of it,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> deliver themſelves in a clean and covered language, when they have occaſion to ſpeake of things leſſe comely. And the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith, he will take the <hi>names</hi> of <hi>Baalim</hi> out of the mouthes of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.17.</note> Oh that the words of uncleanneſſe and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie were taken out of our mouthes. Even <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> in his <hi>Politiques,</hi> would have all <hi>obſceneneſs</hi> of words to be baniſhed
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:54709:66"/>by a Law, becauſe when people take a libertie to <hi>ſpeake ill,</hi> they learn to <hi>doe ill.</hi> He would therefore have ſuch as are <hi>young,</hi> neither to ſpeake or heare any thing that is foule, and if any be found faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be puniſhed with ſtripes, or ſome note of infamie. Oh that <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> would conſider this paſſage of an <hi>heathen,</hi> and be aſhamed. There are many that cannot be <hi>pleaſant,</hi> but they muſt be <hi>obſcene,</hi> and their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (if they have any) is at the beſt <hi>frothy,</hi> but for the moſt part, <hi>wanton.</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:54709:66"/>But they ſay, their tongues are their owne, and who is Lord over them, or who ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule them? Truly they doe confeſſe themſelves to be the children of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> and out of their own mouthes doe condemne themſelves of <hi>madneſse,</hi> in the judgement of the great <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> who when <hi>Feſtus</hi> charged him to be <hi>mad</hi> thorough too much learning, frees him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by this argument;
<note place="margin">Act. 26.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſpeake the words of truth and ſoberneſſe,</hi> or, <hi>the words of a ſound mind.</hi> Surely then by that <hi>rule,</hi> Their
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:54709:67"/>minds are not ſound, whoſe words are not ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. As a prevention of this, I would adviſe all to doe with their looſe and poyſonous <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> and all other <hi>bad bookes,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Converts</hi> of <hi>Epheſus</hi> did with their bookes of <hi>Curious Arts,</hi> bring them forth and <hi>burne</hi> them. I know one that had read many of theſe <hi>toyes,</hi> that took upon himſelfe this <hi>revenge:</hi> a friend of his comming into his <hi>cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> took down from off a ſhelfe a <hi>play-book,</hi> who reading a little was taken with it, and deſired to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:54709:67"/>borrow it: after a while he comes to borrow an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; the owner being ſenſible of his own hurt, and grieved to ſee his friend infected, uſeth this Remedie; <hi>You complained</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>when you came in of cold; I will make you a better ſire.</hi> And preſently (whatſoever his friend could doe to the contrary to hinder him) he takes downe a whole <hi>ſhelfe</hi> of ſuch like bookes and burnes them before him. <hi>This</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have done to puniſh my ſelfe, and to preſerve you.</hi> O that I could perſwade our <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:54709:68"/>and <hi>Gentlewomen,</hi> and all others that miſ-ſpend their pretious <hi>leaſures</hi> to doe the like. Away with your <hi>Amadis</hi> of <hi>Gaule,</hi> your <hi>Palmerins,</hi> your <hi>Mirrour of Knighthood,</hi> with the &amp;c. all of them ſuch <hi>traſh</hi> as is ſcarce worth the inke of two lines wherein they are named: Away with your <hi>Tragedies,</hi> and <hi>Comedies,</hi> and <hi>Maſques,</hi> and <hi>Pasto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals,</hi> &amp; whatſoever other names they have, that ſoften the ſpirit, and take away your ſavour of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly matters: A way with your <hi>Spenſer,</hi> your
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:54709:68"/>
                  <hi>Ariosto,</hi> your deare <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> too, if theſe doe ſteale away your hearts and time from <hi>Scripture-ſtudy</hi> and <hi>Meditation.</hi> I have heard that that <hi>Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> a man worthy of all the honour that is done him, for his <hi>Elegancie</hi> of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> and well and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per contriving of his <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> died with, <hi>Ingenio pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> miſer,</hi> often in his mouth, complaining of his <hi>wit,</hi> that he had left no better monument of it, or of his ſpare houres. We are eaſily <hi>faſhioned</hi> into what we reade much, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:54709:69"/>with delight, as our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies take the qualities of ſuch meat which we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily feed upon. We loſe the repugnancie we have againſt, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of evill; by often reading evill and wanton things. This was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the brave <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians</hi> would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Stage,</hi> and why Antient Chriſtians (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Fathers</hi>) were ſo vehement againſt the Cirque and the <hi>Theater.</hi> I am ſure we had need to urge this point, upon ſuch as live delicately and at eaſe, of whom we may
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:54709:69"/>complaine, as <hi>Strato</hi> the Philoſopher did, that <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedemus</hi> of the <hi>Sect</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picurus</hi> had more Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars then he, becauſe he read <hi>Lectures</hi> of <hi>voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> So many Ladies are farre more acquainted with their <hi>Romance's,</hi> then with the Sacred Hiſtorie; and keep no bookes uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by them, but <hi>Love-ſtories</hi> and <hi>playes.</hi> I could not forbeare this <hi>digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> to paſſe the preſent cenſure. The directive and hortatory part, I ſhall have a better place for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards under the laſt head, concerning Pietie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:54709:70"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The former grace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended. Modeſtie in At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="3">3. LEt the <hi>garments</hi> and <hi>Attire</hi> bemodeſt. I know concerning whom I ſpeake, and what need there is to ſpeake <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>ſharpely</hi> to this point. The contrary is a ſinne of long continuance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deeply rooted. Wee have a full ſtory of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> womens vanitie, in the third chapter of <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> a place that hath often been the <hi>theame</hi> of <hi>Pulpits.</hi> Yet after that time of the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:54709:70"/>
                  <hi>Prophet,</hi> they ſinne more, wee learne by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> that they tooke up <hi>faſhions</hi> from the <hi>Babylonians,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 23.11.</note> She doted</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> under the name of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holah) upon the Aſsyrians her neighbours, clothed moſt gorgeouſlie.</hi> They imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faſhions in portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15</note> 
                  <hi>She ſaw men pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied in the wall, the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Caldeans pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied with virmilion, gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with girdles upon their loines, exceeding in dyed at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire upon their heads.</hi> And ſome do interpret the 16. verſe of that chapter; as
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:54709:71"/>if they had their leigers at <hi>Babylon</hi> to give them Intelligence of the <hi>new deviſes.</hi> As wee have heard of ſome practiſes like it, men ſent and kept in <hi>France, Italie,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, to be the <hi>factors</hi> of <hi>Braverie,</hi> to be ready to ſend over the <hi>Dreſſes.</hi> The conſultation that was had in the ridiculous Senate which <hi>Heliogabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> granted to his <hi>mother</hi> and the <hi>Roman women,</hi> was only upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. And there are ſome (no doubt) that conſult with as much care and earneſtnes about a <hi>dreſse,</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:54709:71"/>as if <hi>A new government</hi> were to be framed and moulded; and are more troubled, if the <hi>handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife</hi> ſit not neately, or an <hi>hayre</hi> be amiſſe, then that the whole ſtate be ruined, and though peace, and religion, and all be loſt. I am not ſo ſtrict about <hi>faſhions,</hi> as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all that are new, I thinke as there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie to ſpeake the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the time, that we may be underſtood, and not to affect <hi>Old Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or <hi>old Engliſh</hi> words when they are grown out of uſe; ſo it is fit that our
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:54709:72"/>
                  <hi>wearing</hi> be like that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, leſt we be noted for affectation of <hi>Singulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is, in <hi>The Hypo citte Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>covered.</hi> l. 1. chap. 7</note> I know no rule that binds us to the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>habits</hi> of old times, for what times muſt we be meaſured by; by that reaſon we muſt riſe higher and higher, till we come to <hi>Adams</hi> time, and <hi>clothe</hi> our ſelves with <hi>ſkinnes.</hi> I would only have the law of <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> in the heart, to give the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this point, wherein if <hi>wantonneſſe,</hi> and too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive <hi>costlineſse</hi> be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, all is obſerved that
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:54709:72"/>is neceſſarie. <hi>Wantonneſse</hi> in apparell, ſeemes to be that <hi>Strangeneſſe,</hi> which the Prophet <hi>Zephanie</hi> ſpeakes of,
<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.8.</note> and which by him the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens to puniſh. And it is one kind of puniſhment, that it robs women of their <hi>Reputation. Claudia</hi> the <hi>Veſtall</hi> though ſhe were innocent, yet was ſuſpected becauſe of her <hi>attire. Seneca</hi> was an <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> yet he ſaw it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be condemned in ſome women in his time, who wore ſuch <hi>garments</hi> as yet in a manner they were <hi>naked</hi> thorough
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:54709:73"/>them. Exceſſive <hi>Coſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi> alſo hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned both by naturall, and Chriſtian light. The <hi>antient Divines</hi> were much againſt it. We can hardly believe almoſt what <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of ſome, <hi>Vno li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no decies ſeſtertium inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur:</hi> that ſome women wore, <hi>A thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fand Seſterces</hi> (which if I have computed rightly, by comparing the old <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> to our <hi>Engliſh mony,</hi> is, ſeven thouſand eight hundred and twelve pound, eight ſhillings) <hi>upon one ſtring.</hi> But <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:54709:73"/>alſo gives in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Vno ſilo villarum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt pretia,</hi> that ſome wore <hi>the priſes of divers Lordſhips in one chaine.</hi> By which wee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand another paſſage of <hi>Tertullians, Saltus &amp; inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las tenera cervix fert.</hi> Truly, ſuch things doe no way befit women profeſſing godlines, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeakes, for thoſe that profeſſe godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe muſt reſolve to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for it, if God call them to it, but as <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> gravely, <hi>I feare</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thoſe neckes hung with
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:54709:74"/>pearle, will not be ſit to lye upon a blocke, to receive the ſword of perſecution.</hi> Oh let thoſe <hi>Ladies,</hi> thoſe brave ones conſider, they profeſſe a <hi>crucified Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> and ſerve not a God crowned with <hi>Roſes</hi> and <hi>Pearles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I inſiſt not much upon this, there is one thing only that I cannot thinke of without indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; nor ſpeake of, but with paſſion, that is, of <hi>Love-ſpots</hi> and <hi>Painting.</hi> Oh the earneſt and holy zeale of the <hi>Antients</hi> againſt this. I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeake in their
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:54709:74"/>words, then mine owne. <hi>Tertullian</hi> bitterly, he cals <hi>painted</hi> women, <hi>Ancillas Diaboli,</hi> The <hi>Devils way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-women;</hi> and urgeth that it is neither agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>Creation</hi> nor the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I once made uſe of, and alluded to a Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of <hi>Cyprians,</hi> in the preſence of ſome great women of qualitie; Suppoſe one ſhould come into the <hi>Kings gallerie,</hi> and daube ſome other colours over a picture that the <hi>King</hi> had hung there, being the work of an excellent <hi>Artiſt,</hi> would
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:54709:75"/>not the <hi>King</hi> be much diſpleaſed at it. You are Gods owne workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, doe ye deſpiſe his hand, that ye preſume to alter it, and pretend to mend it. <hi>Hierome</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting <hi>Laeta</hi> how to bring up her daughter, tels her of a woman that was <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter percuſſa,</hi> the heavie hand of God was upon her, becauſe ſhe ſuffered her daughter to <hi>paint;</hi> and he cals ſuch, The Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Temple of Chriſt, and he loades it with much infamie, that it is, The inflamer of young men, The fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:54709:75"/>of luſts, The diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie of an unchaſt mind. Yea, the <hi>Fathers</hi> doe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſpeake in that manner; When the caſe was put to <hi>Auguſtine</hi> by his friend <hi>Poſsidonius,</hi> he determines it to be an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous fallacie.</hi> And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> goeth ſo farre, that he ſaith it is worſe then Adulterie, and he gives reaſons for it. I am loath to ſpeake ſo fully, but yet I profeſſe my ſelf a very enemie unto it, and ſo I doe to <hi>ſpotting,</hi> upon the ſame grounds.</p>
               <p>But to leave theſe <hi>Pageants,</hi> I returne to my
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:54709:76"/>modeſt woman, I allow her a lawfull difference of apparell, according to the difference of her <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> and <hi>eſtate.</hi> Only I would have them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that they are to give honour to their <hi>Clothes,</hi> and not their <hi>clothes</hi> to them. Let them deſpiſe and renounce the vanities of their Sexe; and as the <hi>Iewiſh women</hi> gave up their <hi>looking-glaſſes</hi> to Gods ſervice,
<note place="margin">Exod. 30.</note> ſo let them give up their <hi>niceneſſe</hi> and <hi>braverie</hi> for heaven. <hi>Elias</hi> neglected his <hi>Mantle</hi> when he went up in the <hi>fiery Chariot,</hi> ſo where the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:54709:76"/>mind is raiſed to an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ambition, there will not be ſo many thoughts of outward decking. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member only, 1. That ſin brought in Clothes. 2. That Clothes are a Monument of our ſhame. 3. That the beſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is that of the <hi>inner man.</hi> Say not then, <hi>This with Lace will doe well;</hi> but this or this will doe well with Diſcretion, Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and Grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:54709:77"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Humility, a Grace of great Ornament. Womans Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The queſtion, whether women may be Teachers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>HVmility.</hi> This is the <hi>ſweeteſt</hi> of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> The fitteſt for great Perſonages. Thoſe <hi>ſtars</hi> that are <hi>higheſt</hi> ſeeme <hi>leaſt.</hi> The <hi>ſea</hi> is not <hi>bigger,</hi> though many <hi>rivers</hi> emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty themſelves into it, and it keepes the ſame taſte and temper, though an abundance of <hi>freſh water</hi> be poured into it out of the clouds. It becomes thoſe upon whoſe <hi>Birth</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:54709:77"/>and <hi>beautie,</hi> both <hi>riches</hi> and <hi>honors</hi> are heaped, to be ſtill the ſame, neither <hi>ſwollen</hi> nor <hi>freſhed.</hi> This grace that makes you low in your own eyes, ſets you high in the ſight of God. For ſo ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> expreſſely, <hi>the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of a meek and quiet ſpirit,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3 4.</note> is in the ſight of God of great price.</hi> It is the moſt attractive, the moſt winning grace. Thus <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> gained upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> and <hi>Abigail</hi> upon <hi>David.</hi> But the greateſt women loſe themſelves by pride. <hi>Iezabel</hi> by her arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie made her ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible:
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:54709:78"/>her owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants threw her out of the window, and ſhe was eaten of doggs. Let great ones conſider, they were made of the <hi>ſame fleſh,</hi> and ſhall be reſolved into the <hi>ſame duſt,</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> could not diſcerne any difference in a <hi>charnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe</hi> betwene the ſculls of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>beggars;</hi> but that which is of moſt weight, is that they ſhall anſwer before the ſame <hi>Eternal Iudge,</hi> at the <hi>ſame tribunall.</hi> Boaſt not of <hi>extraction,</hi> it is not <hi>Birth</hi> but <hi>new birth</hi> that ſhall be availeable. Be not poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:54709:78"/>with <hi>flatteries.</hi> She that is extolled in <hi>verſes,</hi> may be <hi>loathſome</hi> before God. Be not proud of <hi>cloths,</hi> it may be all the worth is in the out-ſide. A <hi>porter</hi> may as well be proud of his <hi>load.</hi> The <hi>walls</hi> of a <hi>chamber</hi> that is covered with <hi>rich han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings,</hi> are in the ſame condition with the back and ſhoulders of a <hi>brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-decked foole.</hi> Challenge not the eyes of every be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, as if it were their duty to doe obeyſance to your <hi>beautie,</hi> for beautie is but <hi>clay well coloured.</hi> As for riches and honors;
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:54709:79"/>a ſneaking <hi>player</hi> might as well be proud of the part he beares upon the <hi>Stage.</hi> You will be <hi>undreſt</hi> in the <hi>Tyring houſe</hi> of the grave, &amp; lay all theſe off. Set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes the great examples of Humilitie. <hi>Ruth</hi> the daughter of the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> if we may receive the generall opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> or if that be not ſo probable, yet one that we may well ſuppoſe to have bin of good qualitie in her own country as being wife of <hi>Mahlon</hi> the elder brother, of the family of Prince <hi>Naaſſon,</hi> yet ſhe accounts
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:54709:79"/>her ſelfe ſcarce equall to one of the maid ſervants in the houſe of <hi>Boaz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ruth 2.13.</note> And <hi>Abigail</hi> ſpeakes the like language,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.41.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith ſhe to <hi>David) let thine hand-maid be a ſervant, to waſh the feet of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of my Lord. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> though the elder woman, and the better for outward qualitie, yet challenged not reſpects and viſits from <hi>Mary,</hi> but was even confounded with it as too great a weight of honor, that <hi>Mary</hi> vouchſafed to come to ſee her,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1, 42.</note> 
                  <hi>Whence is this to mee, that the Mother of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:54709:80"/>my Lord ſhould come to me?</hi> And as for <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelf, when the <hi>Angel</hi> had told her things ſufficient to have overwhelmed a weake ſpirit unable to beare and digeſt honor, She returnes,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.38.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the handmaid of the Lord.</hi> Conſider with what ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this dutie;
<note place="margin">Epheſ 4.1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>I the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner of the Lord, beſeech you, that ye walke worthy of the Vocation wherewith ye are called, with all lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse and meekeneſs,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.12.</note> with longſuffering, forbearing one another in love.</hi> And in another place, <hi>put</hi> on
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:54709:80"/>
                  <hi>(as the elect of God, holy and beloved) bowells of mercies, kindneſse, humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mind, meekeneſſe, longſuffering, forbearing one another.</hi> Theſe are the garments that ſit beſt upon Gods choſen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuch as are holy, and beloved of God;</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>bowells of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Dorcas</hi> is moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for the <hi>coates</hi> which ſhe made for <hi>widdowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Kindneſſe.</hi> This is the exerciſe of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion which is in the bowells. If the heart be open, the hands will not be ſhut.</p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:54709:81"/>
               <p n="3">3. But that which I alleadged this place for, is, <hi>Humbleneſſe of mind.</hi> A grace hardly attained unto, <hi>Many</hi> (ſaith Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,) <hi>can more eaſily give all they have to the poore, then themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come poore in ſpirit.</hi> Nay, oftentimes <hi>pride</hi> takes her riſing out of workes of charity. But the more difficult it is, it is the more needfull. Needfull even in <hi>afflictions</hi> that we mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murre not, nor fret, nor ſwell againſt God: but eſpecially needfull for ſuch as abound or have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eminencie, that God
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:54709:81"/>be not forgotten, and that others be not <hi>deſpiſed.</hi> T'is a rare thing to be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove</hi> others and not to <hi>ſcorne</hi> them.</p>
               <p>Conſider, 1. What e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we have, we have it of God, not of our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the good we have is little in reſpect of that we want.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The more good we have received, the more ſtrict will be our account.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Chriſt</hi> in whom the fulnes of the <hi>Godhead</hi> dwelt, and ſo was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly good, was lowlie and humble.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Lowlineſſe</hi> is <hi>Chriſts</hi>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:54709:82"/>image, and pride a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall part of the <hi>Divels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Pride</hi> is the ſtaine of all graces, and the defacer of every good worke. One that doth ill and is humbled is more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, then one that doth good and is proud.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Gods <hi>gracious eye</hi> is upon an humble heart, but he caſts a <hi>terrible eye</hi> upon ſuch as are proud.</p>
               <p>Beſides this in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, there are only two <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> which I would commend to women, as particularly concerning them in this point. The one is about
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:54709:82"/>their acknowledgement of their <hi>ſubordination</hi> to <hi>man.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.1, 2.</note> Wives</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>be in ſubjection to your own husbands, that if any obey not the Word, they alſo may without the word, be won by the converſation of the wives, while they behold your chaste converſation, coupled with feare:</hi> (that is, with a loving and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fear and reverence of your husband.) Thus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly women in old time were,
<note place="margin">ver. 5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>being in ſubjection unto their own husbands, even as Sarah obeyed Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham calling him Lord, whoſe daughters ye are as
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:54709:83"/>long as ye doe well, and are not afraid with any amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> As excellent as the <hi>woman-Sexe</hi> is, yet it is in ſubjection to man. Even <hi>Sarah</hi> the mother of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, from whom <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> came, called her husband <hi>Lord.</hi> The wife is alſo Lady, for ſo did <hi>Sarah</hi> ſignifie, but ſhe is ſo to the <hi>family,</hi> not to her <hi>husband.</hi> Their <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſaith, that which beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes them, is <hi>to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> and to preſerve and contain themſelves <hi>quiet, indisturbed,</hi> and <hi>unpaſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> not <hi>hurried</hi> with ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:54709:83"/>and inordinate affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as an horſe not well managed that is apt to <hi>ſtart</hi> at every thing. This I take to be the proper meaning of the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Text, which our <hi>Interpreters</hi> have tranſlated, <hi>Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The other place,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4, 35.</note> is that of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Let your women keep ſilence in the Churches, for it is not permitted unto them to ſpeake, but they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be under obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: as alſo ſaith the Law. And if they will learne any thing, let them aske their husbands at home: for it is a
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:54709:84"/>ſhame for women to ſpeake in the Church.</hi> It ſeemes there was ſome diſorder in <hi>Corinth,</hi> and that their women took upon them to ſpeake and teach pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely. This the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> reſtrains. Which he doth upon theſe three grounds; 1. Becauſe of their ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by an originall law. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16. That is the ground which he urgeth in this place. But elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in his writings, he uſeth others alſo. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the woman was created after <hi>Adam,</hi> and for him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8, 9. 3. Becauſe the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:54709:84"/>
                  <hi>woman</hi> was <hi>firſt deceived,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. and 14. But the <hi>Queſtion</hi> will be, what <hi>women</hi> the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſpeakes of: for it was prophecyed of the <hi>Goſpel-times,</hi> That God would poure his Spirit upon all fleſh, and that our ſons and <hi>daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhould prophecie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joel 2.28.</note> And we reade that <hi>Philip</hi> had foure daughters <hi>which did prophecie;</hi> which ſeemes to ſome, to be meant, not of an extraordinary Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Revelation and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction only, (as moſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters</hi> doe put off this place) but of the <hi>interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:54709:85"/>And the rather, becauſe S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> gives a rule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the covering of the womans head, when ſhe is <hi>praying</hi> or <hi>prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5. And in another place he ſpeakes of <hi>Aged women,</hi> that they muſt be <hi>Teachers of good things.</hi> This hath therfore divided the <hi>Antient Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> (for it is not a new Queſtion:) <hi>Chryſostome</hi> thinking that <hi>married wives</hi> are only forbidden to ſpeake in the Church; but <hi>Tertullian</hi> applyes it unto all women, even <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins</hi> and <hi>Widowes</hi> too, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the <hi>univerſall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi>
                  <pb n="359" facs="tcp:54709:85"/>of their <hi>Sexe.</hi> The comparing of the places ſatisfies me; Firſt that is to be laid as an unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſtone in the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That it is againſt <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> againſt <hi>Church Order</hi> and <hi>Modeſty,</hi> for women <hi>publikely</hi> to <hi>preach.</hi> This ground will hold, for the words of the <hi>Apostle</hi> are expreſſe, and will admit of no evaſion. Secondly, There may be ſome extraordinary ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that will not admit of a generall rule. Thirdly, women may and muſt privately and familiarly exhort others. Fourthly,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:54709:86"/>where men are not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, women may ſpeake; I meane, though others beſides the maids and children of their own family be preſent. There are ſome <hi>prints</hi> and <hi>foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps</hi> of the allowance of this in the <hi>Antient Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> They may alſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately admoniſh men, and reprove them. But in the exerciſe of all theſe <hi>Priviledges,</hi> let them have reſpect to the <hi>Law of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,</hi> without which they will never doe any thing <hi>becommingly.</hi> 'Tis a grace of ſuch <hi>neceſsitie</hi> and <hi>beautie,</hi> that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:54709:86"/>too much commend it. I have twice praiſed it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</hi> l. 1. cha. 18. <hi>Help to Chriſtian Fellowſhip.</hi> chap. 7.</note> and eſpecially for one uſe of it, that it diſpoſeth and frameth the ſpirit, to the maintaining of <hi>Chriſtian Fellowſhip,</hi> a duty much neglected, and the more through the want of this grace of Converſation. I might alſo commend it, from the advantage that might be made of it. It is the <hi>Vſher</hi> of <hi>honour. Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> hath ſaid it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.33. and again he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peates it, <hi>Cha.</hi> 18.12. That whereas before deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart is haughty, <hi>Before honour is Humility.</hi>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:54709:87"/>Nay, riches and ſafety al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo attend upon it. As it is in another of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs. <hi>By humility and the feare of the Lord, are riches, and honour, and life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>The Excellencie of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The uſefulneſſe of it. The Maximes of Wiſdome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>WIſdome</hi> and <hi>Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This grace of Converſation is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, that without it, <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is without pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse, according to that which I noted before out
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:54709:87"/>of <hi>Solomon.
<note place="margin">Prov. 11.22.</note> As a Jewel of gold in a ſwines ſnout, ſo is a faire woman which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcretion.</hi> Yet there are many, that have lived to many yeeres, and have learned no skill but only to <hi>dreſſe</hi> themſelves, and to <hi>talke wantonly.</hi> None ever are compleat, unleſſe they be brought up in the <hi>Schoole of Diſcretion.</hi> A Schoole, which as the report goes, that wiſe man the old Lord <hi>Burleigh</hi> ſaid he could not finde, when being in one of the <hi>Vniverſities,</hi> they had ſhewed him all the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Schooles.</hi> It is to be
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:54709:88"/>had from <hi>God,</hi> and to be learnt out of the <hi>book of God,</hi> for ſo ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Let the Word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all wiſdome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> And therefore he writes to the ſame <hi>Coloſsians; We ceaſe not to pray for you,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.9.</note> and to deſire that ye might be filled with the knowledge of his</hi> (Gods) <hi>will, in all wiſdome and ſpirituall understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that ye might walke worthy of the Lord, unto all pleaſing.</hi> The knowledge of Gods will, inſtructs in all kind of wiſedome, to that end that we may walk (for we muſt <hi>walk in
<note place="margin">Col. 4.5.</note>
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:54709:88"/>wiſdome</hi>) as becomes us before God, and with the good acceptance of men. And this higheſt wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, God grants only unto thoſe, upon whom he beſtowes his Sonne <hi>Chriſt;</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes in another Epiſtle,
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.6, 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath made us accepted in the beloved, in whom we have Redemption through his bloud, the forgiveneſſe of ſins, according to the riches of his grace, wherein he hath abounded towards us in all wiſdome and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> It is a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to Learning, to know what <hi>Authors</hi> are
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:54709:89"/>beſt to be <hi>ſtudied;</hi> and as they ſaid concerning <hi>Chriſt, Whence hath this man, this wiſdome?</hi> So, would we not be glad to know what <hi>politiques, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſtudyed, or what authors he read. Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe tels us,
<note place="margin">Pro. 15.33</note> 
                  <hi>The feare of God, is the Inſtruction of wiſdome.</hi> And to the ſame ſenſe his father, <hi>King Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 111.10.</note> had ſaid, <hi>The feare of God, is the beginning of wiſdome.</hi> This is that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the excellencie whereof I would ſet forth, that it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable. We are all apt to deſire <hi>ſilver</hi> and <hi>gold,</hi>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:54709:89"/>for we know the price of them, and therefore we ſearch out the <hi>Veines</hi> of them, and dig for them into the bowells of the earth, even into the <hi>paths</hi> which no foule knoweth, and which the vultures eye hath not ſeene.
<note place="margin">Icb. 28, 12, 13, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>But where ſhall wiſedome be found? Man knoweth not the price thereof. Iob</hi> tells us ſomewhat, but he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell us the full value. <hi>It cannot be gotten for gold, neither ſhall ſilver be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the price thereof. It cannot be valued with the Gold of Ophir, with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Onyx or the Saphire.
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:54709:90"/>The Gold and the Chryſtall cannot equall it, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of it, ſhall not be for Iewels of fine Gold.</hi> All theſe expreſſions are ſhort, theſe things are not worth naming, they may not ſo much as be brought in nomination, when there is ſpeech of the election of wiſedome. for ſo <hi>Iob</hi> goes on. <hi>No mention ſhall be made of Corall or of Pearles; for the price of wiſedome is above Rubies. The Topaz of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia ſhall not equall it, neither ſhall it be valued with pure Gold. Solomon</hi> was a great ſearcher after
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:54709:90"/>
                  <hi>rarities,</hi> but never met with any thing like this to take up his whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. He calleth all other things <hi>folly:</hi> and concludes after a wearie curioſitie,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſaw that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome excelleth folly, as farre as light excelleth darkneſse.</hi> And therefore no wonder, both that he begged it before all things, when God gave him his choyce, and alſo directs all to chuſe it. <hi>Wiſdome is the principall thing, therfore get wiſdome;
<note place="margin">Prov. 4.7.</note> and with all thy getting, get underſtanding.</hi> 'Tis a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain that will make every
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:54709:91"/>one rich. She is a <hi>Lady</hi> that will advance all her kindred: for there is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of this name, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> intimateth, where he ſpeaketh of the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wiſdome.</hi> Boaſt not of other bloud, or ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination; But, <hi>ſay unto wiſdome,
<note place="margin">Prov. 7.4.</note> Thou art my ſiſter, and call understanding thy kinſwoman.</hi> What ſhall I ſay to <hi>Ladies,</hi> and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to women, Would ye have Beautie? If it be true that the <hi>Kingly Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> ſaith of men, <hi>A mans wiſdome maketh his face to ſhine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl 8.1.</note> It is true alſo of women, that wiſdome
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:54709:91"/>will make them beautifull and lovely. Neither is the <hi>uſefulneſse</hi> of wiſdome, leſſe then the excellencie of it. It is the <hi>Compaſſe</hi> without which the <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect</hi> cannot do any thing. It is the <hi>magnetick needle</hi> without which there can be no <hi>Navigation.</hi> It car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the <hi>light</hi> before us, for want of which all that walke in the <hi>darke</hi> muſt needs ſtumble and fall.</p>
               <p>I will not inſiſt upon the difference that the <hi>Schoole</hi> makes, between <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>Prudence.</hi> I am ſpeaking of them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a <hi>Popular</hi> way; It is
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:54709:92"/>that which directs the <hi>Hic</hi> and <hi>Nunc,</hi> it Orders us in particular Caſes. It is that which deliberates upon any thing, that is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it examines all the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of a <hi>deſigne,</hi> that nothing be done raſhly, but ſo that a good account may be given of the doing of any thing, if it be called for. It gives a <hi>good grace</hi> to every <hi>poſture.</hi> Every paſſion or inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affection diſguiſeth. <hi>Malice</hi> hath a ſullen and <hi>down-look</hi> which diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling can hardly hide; <hi>Anger</hi> appeares upon the knitted brow; <hi>Deſire</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:54709:92"/>it ſelfe in the eye; but <hi>Prudence</hi> keepes in all theſe that would gad abroad into the viſage to tell what <hi>newes</hi> within. But a ſpeciall uſe of it is, that it corrects the ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſneſs of <hi>affectation</hi> and <hi>artificialneſſe.</hi> There is nothing more vaine then a <hi>forced</hi> art of <hi>ſeeming wiſe,</hi> when laughter, ſpeech, geſture, and every thing is <hi>con'd</hi> and <hi>ſtudied.</hi> This is <hi>ſlaviſhneſse,</hi> not <hi>wiſdome. Wiſdome</hi> leades on all <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> with a kind of <hi>native<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi> and <hi>honeſt freedome.</hi> The others that have all their <hi>words</hi> out of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionarie,</hi>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:54709:93"/>and their <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures</hi> from the <hi>glaſse,</hi> are alwayes in feare, and if they happen to be out, (like <hi>formall Preachers</hi> that have got a <hi>Set</hi> of <hi>ſtrong lines</hi> into their memorie) they can hardly recover themſelves, but talk <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>gibbriſh.</hi> Shall I offer at the deſcription of this prudence; It is a grace teaching the heart a <hi>deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> in religious and civill Converſation, as having deliberated, and knowing what our <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions</hi> will beare, or are fit to refuſe, whereby we may carry our ſelves
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:54709:93"/>right alſo in the uſe of things indifferent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceſſe or defect, and in the uſe of Chriſtian Policie with pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbed Conſciences.</p>
               <p>It were to write ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther booke to give the particular adviſes of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Take things ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and as they come, it may be without method.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Make <hi>memorie</hi> a <hi>ſtorehouſe.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe we cannot ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, eaſily, be wiſe without others wiſdome.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Study men and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. Know the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion</hi> of affaires.</p>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:54709:94"/>
               <p n="3">3. Be willing to learne of ſuch as are faithfull and that drive no trade or intereſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Stand behind the picture, and heare what they ſay that paſſe by.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Deſpiſe not a Cobler in what he ſayes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſhooe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Beleeve not others <hi>flatteries</hi> againſt your own knowledge.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Beleeve you may have imperfections.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Take heed of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which diſcoulers all things.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Runne not downe a ſteep bank; conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:54709:94"/>you may ſtay, when you have a mind to ſtay, or are out of breath.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Know that <hi>Selfe-conceit</hi> puts out ones eyes.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Before ye ſet out, diſcover whether there be any ambuſhments.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Conſider how much better it is to <hi>knit</hi> then <hi>bloſſome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Make not too much haſte, leſt ye out-run the buſineſſe. Speed is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangler, and haſte is ſlow.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Eſteeme <hi>Honeſtie</hi> to be the firſt and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall part of wiſdome.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Never account an <hi>unequall, wavering, ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorie</hi>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:54709:95"/>humour of <hi>comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to be either <hi>honeſtie</hi> or <hi>wiſdome.</hi> Such as look at the <hi>Times</hi> are honeſt ſometimes only by <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> and as it <hi>hits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. Honeſtie is a free, generous, uniforme, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved walking accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to right Principles, whatere others think of it.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Account the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wavering honeſtie of <hi>Formaliſts,</hi> to be a <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danticall folly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. Reſolve upon ſome <hi>Marke,</hi> at which all you doe may have a <hi>conſtant aime. Fooles</hi> only live at <hi>randome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:54709:95"/>
               <p n="19">19. Think not of ſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king arrowes in the <hi>clouds.</hi> Attempt not what may not be attained.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Think not of <hi>bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing</hi> deſires and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but of <hi>governing</hi> them.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Be moderate and equall in adverſities and proſperitie. Diſtruſt your ſtrength moſt in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Be not perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but rather accuſtome your ſelves to the old forme of <hi>Ita videtur; So it ſeemes to me,</hi> rather then to ſay, <hi>So it is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. Tremble not at a
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:54709:96"/>
                  <hi>ſcoffe.</hi> 'Tis weakneſſe to leave vertue, becauſe others like it not.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Be <hi>pertinent</hi> in ſpeech, rather then <hi>large.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="25">25. Penetrate into the <hi>ſpirits</hi> and <hi>diſpoſitions</hi> of ſuch, as you chooſe for acquaintance of <hi>trust.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. Give not value to things according to the <hi>Market-price.</hi> The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſometimes cry up worthleſſe things, and undervalue rich.</p>
               <p n="27">27. Beleeve not the <hi>croud.</hi> Credit one that hath his eyes, rather then an hundred blind men.</p>
               <p n="28">28. Prefer <hi>Eternity</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:54709:96"/>this <hi>moment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="29">29. Loſe not that you hold, for a ſhadow that you ſee of greater.</p>
               <p n="30">30. Live ſo, as not to be aſhamed to <hi>live longer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might be plentifull; but I take off my hand. In ſtead of all theſe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximes,</hi> the Law of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would ſerve. The <hi>Storie</hi> is, that a King of <hi>France,</hi> one day required of a <hi>great Councellour,</hi> an <hi>antient Stateſman,</hi> that he ſhould ſet downe ſome rules of wiſedome and ſtate: he undertook it, and in a large ſheet of Paper, wrote only <hi>Modus</hi> in
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:54709:97"/>great letters, and wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it up, delivered it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hand of the King, implying that if he could obſerve <hi>Temper,</hi> it would be inſtead of all particular directions. So for the frame of converſation, I would only write, <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Silence a great proofe of wiſedom. The hatefulneſſe of Diſſimulation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is one particular concerning <hi>wiſedom</hi> in <hi>women,</hi> that I may not forget, that is <hi>Silence.</hi> It
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:54709:97"/>was one of the <hi>Qualities</hi> which the wiſe <hi>Socrates</hi> required in his ſchollers; and the old <hi>Romans</hi> ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Altars</hi> to it. It is a rare ornament, eſpecially of <hi>Knowing women,</hi> when they have the ſkill, not to ſpeake all that might be ſpoken; and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that <hi>diſcretion</hi> as it is more difficult ſo it is better then <hi>Eloquence.</hi> Some have thought <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> to be to <hi>ſpeech,</hi> as <hi>Shadow</hi> is to a <hi>picture,</hi> without which it cannot be well ſet off; and as the <hi>Reſts</hi> are to <hi>Muſick,</hi> which make it to be much more
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:54709:98"/>reliſhing and ſweet. They cannot be <hi>wiſe</hi> that talke much, for <hi>hearing</hi> is the <hi>learning Senſe,</hi> and they will not have the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>heare</hi> much. The <hi>Apſtle,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Iames</hi> in that ſame Chapter where he had ſayd,
<note place="margin">Jam. 1.19.</note> 
                  <hi>If any of you lack wiſedom, aske it of God;</hi> ſoon after gives this rule, <hi>Be ſwift to heare, ſlow to ſpeake,</hi> Implying ſurely, That indeed God gives wiſedom, but ordinarily by the meanes of others tongues. But leaſt I ſeeme to diſarme them, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy them the uſe of their beſt weapon; it ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:54709:98"/>that I have only na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this particular, I will forbeare to enlarge it.</p>
               <p>I have only one thing put in by way of Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, concerning <hi>wiſedom,</hi> that under that name, there be not a learning of <hi>Diſſimulation.</hi> It is ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed, and lookes ſo like to <hi>wiſedom,</hi> that one may eaſily be deceived. There are ſome that doe not miſtake, but profeſſe and are not aſhamed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that they goe to this <hi>Schoole.</hi> We know what <hi>Prince</hi> it was that ſaid, he would have his
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:54709:99"/>ſonne learne no more <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> then that, <hi>He that knowes not how to diſsemble knowes not how to live.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny blame his ſpeech, but yet they practiſe upon his <hi>principle.</hi> They ſtudy <hi>vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> and <hi>diſguiſing</hi> of their thoughts. We meet ſome of theſe <hi>darke lanthorns</hi> ſometimes, they will give one leave almoſt to come neare them, by the light they hold forth; and we think we know where to find them, by the <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations</hi> and <hi>profers</hi> they make; but preſently they turne the <hi>darke ſide,</hi> and we looſe them, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:54709:99"/>find out their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. This makes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation ſo unſafe, and ſo difficult, for if diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling had no more <hi>faces</hi> then one; as <hi>truth</hi> hath, we ſhould be in better termes then we are; for whatſoever a <hi>lyer</hi> or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler</hi> ſhould ſay or doe, we would take it in a quite contrarie ſenſe. But this oppoſite of Truth, hath <hi>many-many faces,</hi> T'is a ſtrange art, that <hi>words</hi> which were inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to expreſſe and cleare the thought, are now put to another contrary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, handſomely to hide
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:54709:100"/>them. I confeſſe that in evill and ſnaring times, <hi>Innocencie</hi> may have need of a <hi>maſque,</hi> for it may be a folly to ſhew an <hi>open heart</hi> among many <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhments.</hi> We are not bound to ſpeake or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale all truths at all times. But take heed of craving <hi>Ayde</hi> for <hi>Securitie</hi> of <hi>falſehood.</hi> Honeſtie is better then craft. Some Naturaliſts have told us of a ſtrange fiſh, The <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranoſcope,</hi> that hath but one eye, and that is <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> directly on the top of the head, but with that one eye ſhe keepeth
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:54709:100"/>her ſelfe from all daſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and cruſhes againſt the rockes, and ſees all the approaches of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. <hi>One eye,</hi> if it be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Heaven, is much better and ſurer, then <hi>two</hi> of the quickeſt ſights of ſuch as have all of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and nothing at all of the <hi>Dove.</hi> We have ſeen many of the moſt ſubtle diſſemblers, <hi>entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi> themſelves into ruine, and <hi>bruſh</hi> themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rockes hidden from them, before they were aware. And certainly it is a thing full of <hi>unquiet feares,</hi> and it cannot be
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:54709:101"/>but painfull, to live under a <hi>canopie.</hi> There is the greateſt pleaſure in the <hi>freedome</hi> of <hi>Sincere hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it may be ſaid, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am ſpeaking to men, to <hi>Polititians</hi> all this while, not to women. Nay, I have not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the <hi>Subject</hi> of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. The Sinne which I am making odious, is thought to be very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to women. But I am very angry with thoſe <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> that have given a kind of allowance, unto <hi>Princes,</hi> and unto <hi>women</hi> to counterfeit. I thinke it
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:54709:101"/>is not ſound doctrine in <hi>policie</hi> and <hi>morallity,</hi> I am ſure it is ſtarke naught in <hi>Divinitie.</hi> If people knew thoroughly the <hi>evill</hi> of <hi>lying,</hi> they would purſue it with fire and ſword, till they had <hi>baniſht</hi> it out of the world. There is not in any thing a greater contrarietie to God, for it is contrarie not only to his will, but to his very <hi>nature,</hi> for he is <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe, and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He cannot lye,</hi> for then he ſhould deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.
<note place="margin">Job 8.44.</note> The <hi>Divell</hi> is ſaid to be the father of it. He taught it firſt to <hi>Eve,</hi> and
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:54709:102"/>he ſtill cheriſheth it, as the ſureſt <hi>pillar</hi> of his <hi>dark kingdome.</hi> God hates it, yea, he hates it with a loathing.
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Lying lips are an abomination to the Lord.</hi> It is a ſinne againſt the <hi>good</hi> of <hi>humane Societie:</hi> for <hi>truth</hi> is the foundation of <hi>juſtice,</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> of <hi>peace. Darke</hi> people doe all the miſchiefe. But for reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. 1. Conſider your dignitie. There is a ſaying in better <hi>authours</hi> then thoſe I blamed even now, <hi>That the ſimple word of a Prince ſhould be of as great force, as the eath of a private man.</hi> Let <hi>Ladies</hi>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:54709:102"/>and great women; yea, all women have it in their thoughts, that they were made after the <hi>Image</hi> of God, which is <hi>truth.</hi> It will not become thoſe <hi>ſmooth foreheads,</hi> to have <hi>rough,</hi> and <hi>ſhaddowy,</hi> and <hi>clouded</hi> intentions. What ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul?
<note place="margin">Col. 3.9, 10.</note> Lye not one to another, ſeeing that ye have put off the old man with his deeds, and have put on the new man, which is renewed in knowledge, after the Image of him that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him.</hi> 2. Conſider, That a deceiver forfeits reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. You ſhall bind all alwayes to <hi>miſtruſt,</hi> never
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:54709:103"/>to <hi>beleeve</hi> you. 3. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That <hi>treacherie</hi> is in ſome reſpect beyond <hi>Atheiſme.</hi> It is worſe to <hi>owne</hi> God, and yet to <hi>mocke</hi> him, then not to acknowledge him; for this is, to give a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the contempt of God, and of the fearing of men before him. 'Tis baſe, to be a <hi>Coward</hi> to men, and <hi>ſtout</hi> to God. But I have dealt ſo fully with this ſinne, in <hi>The Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite Diſcovered,</hi> that I now forbeare to enlarge any farther upon this point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:54709:103"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>The beautie of holineſſe. The Rule of Devotion. A ſerious exhortation to the Reading of the Scripture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>PIetie</hi> and <hi>Religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> This is of all others the moſt <hi>Orient</hi> and full of brightneſſe. They ſay that <hi>Jewels</hi> ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in <hi>Honey</hi> have more <hi>lustre;</hi> ſo all accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are made more beautifull by Pietie. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe though a <hi>woman</hi> were ſo made up, that as another <hi>Pandora,</hi> ſhe had all morall graces and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:54709:104"/>beſtowed upon her, yet ſhe would be wretched and unworthy without this. If one had a <hi>Cabinet</hi> made all of <hi>pure gold,</hi> enameled and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, ſet about every where with <hi>Diamonds</hi> and large <hi>Pearles</hi> on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and that the curioſity and exquiſiteneſſe of the <hi>workmanſhip,</hi> ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the richneſſe of the matter; would not every body think the owner of this <hi>Cabinet</hi> worſe then mad, that ſhould ſill it with <hi>dirt</hi> and <hi>filth,</hi> or put it to no other uſe, then to keepe <hi>nasty rags,</hi> or <hi>little
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:54709:104"/>ſtickes</hi> and <hi>ſtrawes.</hi> Such are thoſe <hi>excellent pieces</hi> that are of a <hi>goodly out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward frame,</hi> of winning behaviour, of ſeeming modeſtie, ſweet in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, wiſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in diſcourſe, but within <hi>proſane, irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and without any <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> of <hi>Godlineſse.
<note place="margin">Zech. 15.7. 1 Chr. 16.19. Iſal. 50.2.</note> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> is <hi>Beautie.</hi> The true worſhip of God is call'd ſo, by the Prophet <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and by <hi>David:</hi> yea, the <hi>Perfection of Beautie.</hi> The Apoſtle hath wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed it of Goſpel Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. that the <hi>Miniſtration</hi> of <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:54709:105"/>exceeds in glory.</hi> And he tels us, in the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth verſe, that one cannot be converſant in thoſe Ordinances, but he ſhall receive a luſtre from them; that as <hi>Moſes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with God, and ſeeing God, came away with a ſhining face; <hi>So we all with open face beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame image, from glory to glory, even as by the ſpirit of the Lord.</hi> God himſelf is <hi>glorious in holineſſe,</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſang it unto his praiſe, when they came forth of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex. 15.11.</note> And
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:54709:105"/>the Apoſtle tels us, that the <hi>Graces</hi> which are the <hi>Daughters</hi> of Gods <hi>Spirit,</hi> are <hi>lovely.
<note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note> Whatſoever things are lovely,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if there be any vertue, think on theſe things.</hi> We ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times commend a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious piece in <hi>Picture,</hi> it drawes and entices a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing eye. But as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid, if <hi>Vertue</hi> could be drawne, every one would love it: ſo if it were poſſible to ſhadow out the true <hi>Lincaments</hi> of <hi>Holineſſe</hi> to the eye, who would not be ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with delight? I confeſſe I doe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:54709:106"/>love a <hi>Picture,</hi> when it is done by a <hi>good hand.</hi> But me thinks none can come neare, A <hi>Mary</hi> alone in Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, A <hi>Magdalene</hi> weeping, A <hi>Lydia</hi> attending with much earneſtneſſe to the Word. Oh imagine but the <hi>Beautie,</hi> of the <hi>Tecla's,</hi> the <hi>Marcella's,</hi> the <hi>Paula's,</hi> the <hi>Eustochium's,</hi> the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biola's,</hi> the <hi>Eudoxia's,</hi> emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and famous in their generations for Pietie. Some thinke <hi>Religious Circumſpection</hi> makes <hi>bad</hi> and <hi>darke faces. Diſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling formalitie</hi> will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed oft-times ſtudy a
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:54709:106"/>diſguiſed ſowreneſſe; but <hi>Godlineſse,</hi> though it will be the <hi>Miſtreſse</hi> of the <hi>looks</hi> and <hi>dreſse,</hi> and make all compoſed and ſober, yet it doth nothing to <hi>ſcare</hi> one away, or to <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright</hi> any from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame vertues.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Bodies Beautie</hi> compared with the <hi>Souls,</hi> is as if one ſhould equall a <hi>Torch</hi> to the <hi>Sunne.</hi> The body is but as the <hi>greene Moſse</hi> on the ſide of a <hi>Rocke,</hi> the Soul is the <hi>Diamond</hi> that <hi>ſparkles</hi> within it. Oh that the principall care were for the ſetting forth and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:54709:107"/>this Beautie. It was a Law that <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> made, that none ſhould erect any <hi>Marbles,</hi> or <hi>Columnes,</hi> or other <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities</hi> of <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> in the <hi>Suburbs,</hi> or Countrey vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages; becauſe he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the City of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> ſhould be full of <hi>Ornaments,</hi> and the rich Store-houſe of thoſe <hi>collections.</hi> What then do they deſerve, that forget and forſake, and rob the <hi>inward City,</hi> the <hi>Soul;</hi> to beſtow their <hi>Iewels</hi> upon their <hi>eares,</hi> their <hi>foreheads,</hi> their <hi>brests,</hi> which are but only the <hi>Souls ſuburbs?</hi>
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:54709:107"/>What ſtrange creatures are they, that dreſſe up the <hi>hand-maids,</hi> and ſuffer the <hi>Mistreſſe</hi> to goe in <hi>ragges?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is it then, that I have reſerved to the laſt place to commend. That there may be a ſpeciall endeavour of <hi>Holineſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.11</note> A <hi>holy Converſation,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> cals it;
<note place="margin">Jam. 3.13.</note> A <hi>good Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as <hi>Iames;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 50.23</note> A <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation ordered aright;</hi> as <hi>David</hi> expreſſeth it. But in other Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Gen. 5.24.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1. Luke 1.6.</note> it is ſaid to be a <hi>walking with God.</hi> It muſt be according to Gods will and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. For otherwiſe <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion</hi>
                  <pb n="204" facs="tcp:54709:108"/>is ſubject to many <hi>illuſions.</hi> Nothing is more <hi>counterfeited</hi> or <hi>disfigured</hi> then <hi>Religion.</hi> As the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians</hi> dreſſed up their Gods, after the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion</hi> of the City: ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny make up a Religion after their own humour. I have much wondred to heare of the <hi>ſtrange</hi> and <hi>odde</hi> apprehenſions of Religion, in ſome great perſonages; who had found out a way of joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God and pleaſures together. And had made it almoſt all one, to ſerve God, and entertain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at a <hi>Maſque. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>
                  <pb n="205" facs="tcp:54709:108"/>tels us of <hi>Marcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> that ſhe hung <hi>Christs</hi> picture, and the picture of <hi>Pythagor as</hi> together. And we have heard of ſome <hi>popiſh Ladies,</hi> that have had the ſame curioſities about their <hi>Diſciplining whips,</hi> as about their <hi>fannes,</hi> their <hi>praying beads</hi> as rich as their <hi>neck-laces</hi> and <hi>bracelets,</hi> and their <hi>Crucifixes</hi> made into <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els.</hi> Judge whether this be not rather a <hi>courting</hi> of pleaſure, then the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> And it was much like this that we were come unto; when the great buſineſſe
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:54709:109"/>of Religion, was only to have a <hi>Chappell</hi> or <hi>Cloſet,</hi> decked with <hi>Pictures, Plate,</hi> rich <hi>Cuſhions</hi> and <hi>Clothes.</hi> And the <hi>worſhip,</hi> but only the <hi>varying</hi> of the pleaſures of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-roome,</hi> into another <hi>name.</hi> Or to inſtance in another particular, Shall we think it to be enough to have <hi>Bibles</hi> of all vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnes, larger, and for the Pocket, neatly <hi>bound up,</hi> and <hi>trimmed,</hi> richly <hi>claſped</hi> or <hi>ſtrung,</hi> and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or never to looke into them? Oh, in ſtead of <hi>pompe,</hi> ſtudie inward Sanctification. Approve
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:54709:109"/>your ſelves to God, like ſome <hi>Rivers</hi> that run un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ground, and ſteale from the eyes of the world. They are the moſt excellent ſpirits that beare <hi>much fruit,</hi> but make not <hi>much noyſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Holines</hi> is the end of our <hi>election,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 1.4. 1 Pet. 1.15.</note> God hath choſen us that we ſhould be holy. We ſerve an holy God, Therefore ſaith S <hi>Peter, As he which hath called you is holy, ſo be yee holy in all manner of converſation.</hi> No ſervice is acceptable unles it be holy.
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1</note> 
                  <hi>I beſeech you that ye preſent a living Sacrifice,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:54709:110"/>holy, and acceptable unto God.</hi> We are called to an holy calling. <hi>Ye are an holy nation,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9</note> that ye ſhould ſhew forth the praiſes of him, who hath called you out of darkneſs into his marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous light.</hi> Holines is the ſumme of Chriſts do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. <hi>Ye know the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments wee gave you by the Lord Ieſus,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.3, 4.</note> for this is the will of God, even your Sanctification.</hi> None but the holy can have confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in prayer.
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Let us draw neare with a true heart in full aſsurance of faith, having our hearts ſprinkled from an evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:54709:110"/>There can be no hope of Heaven maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without holineſſe. <hi>Every one that hath this hope in him,
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.3.</note> purifyeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, even as God is pure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This holineſſe muſt be according to Gods holy word. We may not be <hi>Voluntaries in Humilitie. Mantius</hi> who was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in cheife in the <hi>Roman Army,</hi> put his ſon to death, though he got a notable <hi>victorie,</hi> becauſe he did it beyond <hi>commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> We may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume againſt Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed order. <hi>Kings</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the manner of their
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:54709:111"/>owne <hi>ſervice. God</hi> is <hi>Lord,</hi> we muſt looke to the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>his houſe.</hi> If we take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other libertie, there will be much uncettain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and change. Doe all things as neare as may be, by a <hi>warrant</hi> from the <hi>word.</hi> Let me therefore ſeriouſly commend in the firſt place, the conſtant and diligent <hi>Reading</hi> of the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi> Let <hi>women</hi> herein beſtow their happy leaſures. They may doe it. Let no <hi>popiſh envy</hi> deprive you of this faire priviledge. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> for the hands of ſuch whom I
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:54709:111"/>ſuppoſe to be cleared ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently in this <hi>controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie,</hi> and that know their owne <hi>right,</hi> and with what <hi>injuriouſnes</hi> the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> have indeavoured to ſhut up the <hi>Bible</hi> from them. Beleeve not their <hi>politique</hi> and <hi>envious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills.</hi> They ſay it is not <hi>convenient</hi> or <hi>decent</hi> for women to reade ſome paſſages, which may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion evill and <hi>light</hi> thoughts, As the ſtorie of <hi>Lot,</hi> and that of <hi>Leah</hi> ſtriving for <hi>Iacobs</hi> bed, and ſome others which theſe <hi>blaſphemers</hi> are wont to inſtance in. But <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi>
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:54709:112"/>thought, that <hi>Laeta's</hi> daughter though a <hi>Virgin</hi> might ſafelie and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie reade even thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And if their be any relation of <hi>facts</hi> diſhoneſt and uncomely, there is beſides enough to <hi>repreſſe</hi> any diſhoneſt motions that may ariſe upon ſuch occaſion. And if the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument were good, then not only <hi>women,</hi> but <hi>men</hi> alſo the beſt and moſt learned ſhould be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to reade, for they may alſo have the <hi>tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of <hi>unholy thoughts.</hi> They ſay again, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places are too <hi>hard</hi> for
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:54709:112"/>
                  <hi>women</hi> to underſtand. But there are other places, <hi>plaine</hi> and <hi>eaſie.</hi> And if the <hi>Scriptures</hi> were not to be read at all; becauſe all cannot be underſtood by women, then <hi>none</hi> may reade them, for <hi>no man</hi> can perhaps underſtand all that he reades. But let us turne the <hi>Argument,</hi> If the Scriptures be hard to be underſtood, let us therefore reade them the <hi>oftner,</hi> and with more <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</hi> They ſay beſides, there is much danger of <hi>error.</hi> Ah how unlike theſe <hi>Romiſh ſpirits</hi> are, to the <hi>Antient holy Divines.</hi>
                  <pb n="214" facs="tcp:54709:113"/>Their endeavour was to heape up the <hi>benefits,</hi> but the buſineſſe of theſe men, is to <hi>load</hi> the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> with <hi>reproaches</hi> and <hi>diſgraces.</hi> T'is a ſhreud preſumption againſt them that they are <hi>unſound.</hi> They had a <hi>rich trade,</hi> as long as they could keep the <hi>Bible claſpt.</hi> In theſe latter times they have bin forced much againſt their wills, to permit the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> in ſome places, like <hi>Adrian</hi> the <hi>Emperor,</hi> who ſet ſome <hi>Countries</hi> at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, becauſe he was unable to hold them in ſubjection.</p>
               <pb n="215" facs="tcp:54709:113"/>
               <p>But to leave theſe <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe</hi> and <hi>hell;</hi> oh be exhorted, to walke in the ſteps of the <hi>holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Christians. Euſebius</hi> tells us concerning <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus</hi> the <hi>Martyr,</hi> of his <hi>liberalitie,</hi> and among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, that he was wont to beſtow <hi>Bibles</hi> and other <hi>good bookes</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on poore women a moſt commendable <hi>Almes,</hi> and which he would not have beſtowed, had he thought it unfit for <hi>women</hi> to reade. It appeares by <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Nazienzen's</hi> praiſes of his ſiſter <hi>Gorgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> that though ſhe were
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:54709:114"/>a <hi>married woman,</hi> ſhe found much time for <hi>reading. Hierome</hi> giving adviſes to <hi>Laeta</hi> how to inſtitute her daughter, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects her in a courſe, firſt to reade the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> then the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> then <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiastes,</hi> then the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists,</hi> the <hi>Acts,</hi> the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and after theſe the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Five bookes of Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Hiſtoricall</hi> bookes; and leaves it to the <hi>mother</hi> to inſtruct her, or in cafe ſhe were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to the <hi>Aunt.</hi> He prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>Marcella,</hi> that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came to her, but ſhe was asking him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:54709:114"/>about the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> and tells us, that if him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had any doubt, he would ask her <hi>Iudgement.</hi> In the <hi>Epitaph</hi> which he wrote upon <hi>Paula,</hi> he ſaith ſhe had the <hi>Bible</hi> in her memorie. One other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I cannot omit of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roms,</hi> whereby it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that he would not have <hi>women</hi> omit any part of the whole <hi>Bible,</hi> for he finds ſome fault with <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſia,</hi> when ſhe ſent ſome queſtions to him, only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Goſpells,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> writings, that he feared ſhe was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Old
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:54709:115"/>Teſtament.</hi> I will content my ſelfe to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded theſe <hi>antient</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, I might alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in modern, I have in particular taken notice of one notable patterne, namely <hi>Magdalen</hi> the wife of <hi>D. Pareus</hi> of <hi>Heidleberg,</hi> in my <hi>Exercitation upon Malachy,</hi> Chap. 14. v. 14. where by <hi>Digreſsion</hi> I have ſpoken ſomewhat to this point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>The Maximes of Pietie. The Concluſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving put the <hi>Bible</hi> into your hands,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:54709:115"/>with a perſwaſion to ſit down to reade it, I might forbeare to give any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>direction,</hi> becauſe there you will find all that is neceſſarie, neither doe I intend to write an <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian women.</hi> I ſhall therefore only give ſome briefe <hi>Adviſo's,</hi> as they offer themſelves, it may be without any preciſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or method.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Doe all things in <hi>Religion</hi> by rule; nothing by <hi>venture,</hi> hit or miſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let not your rule be <hi>vox populi,</hi> but <hi>verbum Dei,</hi> not the opinion of
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:54709:116"/>the Times, but the uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Truth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Do not <hi>bend</hi> the rule, and then <hi>meaſure</hi> by it. Bring your <hi>Actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> to that, &amp; not that to your <hi>actions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If the caſe be hard, <hi>adviſe.</hi> The truth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>lyes deep,</hi> you will need help to draw it up.</p>
               <p>Particularly:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learne to <hi>know</hi> God. Be not at a doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Baal</hi> be he. You muſt know the <hi>landlord</hi> to whom your <hi>rent</hi> is to be pay'd.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Frame in your hearts, the <hi>higheſt</hi> and <hi>holyeſt</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of him.</p>
               <pb n="221" facs="tcp:54709:116"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Believe</hi> him, <hi>hope</hi> in him, <hi>fe are</hi> him, <hi>love</hi> him, <hi>obey</hi> him, <hi>joy</hi> in him, count it an <hi>honor</hi> to be his <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Keepe an account, and a <hi>watch</hi> over the <hi>thoughts.</hi> Say not <hi>Thoughts are free,</hi> Know that they <hi>defile</hi> one. 5. Baniſh vain, diſorder'd, profane, wanton, proud, malicious thoughts.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Seaſon and fill the thoughts with <hi>holy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi> If they be reve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, thinke how meeke <hi>Chriſt</hi> was, If they be <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious,</hi> thinke thus, <hi>Ah how bad am I my ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The <hi>Imagination</hi> is
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:54709:117"/>a great <hi>thorough-fare:</hi> keep out bad, at leaſt let them not <hi>lodge</hi> with you; but go on as <hi>Vagrants,</hi> leſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you be under the <hi>Statute</hi> and a <hi>penaltie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Get governed and bridled <hi>Affections.</hi> Let them never run out, unles you be ſure they are right. Say, <hi>Anger</hi> is too good for injuries; and <hi>ſorrow</hi> too good for any thing but ſinne; and <hi>love</hi> too good for <hi>luſts</hi> or <hi>mony;</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> too good for earth, or any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Heaven.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Converſe much with God. Let thoſe that
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:54709:117"/>are <hi>carnall</hi> and <hi>unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> with God, entertaine themſelves with the <hi>Stage</hi> or with the <hi>Market.</hi> Be higher then thoſe <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights,</hi> and thoſe <hi>gaines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Live by faith.</hi> Let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that know not this <hi>name</hi> of the <hi>Lord, ſhuffle</hi> in the world, looke to, and provide for themſelves.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Beleeve Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and deliverie if in miſerie. <hi>Fret not.</hi> Thinke how <hi>wiſe</hi> God is, and how <hi>tender.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. Wait upon God for <hi>Grace,</hi> the ſtrength, perfecting, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it.</p>
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:54709:118"/>
               <p n="13">13. Set God before you in all the <hi>turnes</hi> and accidents of buſineſſe and life. Say, <hi>God ſees me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Correſpond</hi> with God in an ordinary and daily walking with him. Make <hi>Religion</hi> your <hi>buſineſse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Awake</hi> with <hi>God.</hi> The world will not ſuffer ſome to ſleep; they ſay, <hi>Oh I must up about ſuch a matter;</hi> Say thou, <hi>I have my God to ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Examine Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> diligently, faithfully, and frequently: Put not out that <hi>Candle,</hi> but rather light up more.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Seeke <hi>Gods face</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:54709:118"/>for pardon and grace.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Renew Covenant</hi> daily.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>Finiſh</hi> every day with <hi>humbling</hi> the Soule.</p>
               <p n="20">20. In extraordinarie occaſions be affected as the <hi>Church</hi> is.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Get <hi>Publike ſpirits.</hi> Such as are worldly, are narrow, and ſleight, and poore; They only attend their own <hi>buſineſse,</hi> how to <hi>live</hi> and <hi>eate,</hi> how to grow <hi>rich,</hi> how to <hi>marry</hi> their children. Be larger and higher then theſe.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Converſe <hi>holily</hi> in the <hi>world.</hi> Be afraid of a light, vaine, <hi>frothy</hi> ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="23">23. Be holy in <hi>relations:</hi>
                  <pb n="226" facs="tcp:54709:119"/>as a wife, daughter, ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, friend, or Companion.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Be choyce of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie,</hi> and <hi>uſefull</hi> in it.</p>
               <p n="25">25. Seaſon all <hi>liberties</hi> and <hi>lawfull Recreations</hi> with Grace. Chuſe to <hi>play</hi> with ſuch, with whom ye may alſo <hi>pray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. Be much in <hi>Publike Worſhip.</hi> Conſider, 'Tis a bleſſing to any place, to have the <hi>conveniencie</hi> of <hi>Aſſembling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27. Come <hi>awefully</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, when you come to his <hi>worſhip.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <hi>That God is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and thou upon earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28. Make <hi>haſt,</hi> ſtay not
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:54709:119"/>for the other <hi>pin.</hi> Let your <hi>cloths</hi> ſit looſe, rather then your <hi>ſoul,</hi> when you come before God in publike.</p>
               <p n="29">29. Pray with the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> joyning in the ſame ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="30">30. Keep up the eſteem of <hi>prayer</hi> which God hath put upon it. Account that God gives you the <hi>Key</hi> of all his <hi>Cabinets,</hi> when he gives you the ſpirit of prayer.</p>
               <p n="31">31. Beware of <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> of <hi>lip-labor,</hi> of <hi>bead-prayer,</hi> come to <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Chriſt</hi> by a Promiſe, in the ſenſe of wants, and in Faith.</p>
               <p n="32">32. <hi>Sing</hi> Gods Praiſes
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:54709:120"/>with underſtanding, and ſpirituall chearfulneſſe.</p>
               <p n="33">33. <hi>Heare</hi> the Word of God, as the Word of God; with ſilence, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, faith, ſubjection.</p>
               <p n="34">34. Care eſpecially for that in a <hi>Sermon,</hi> that doth the Soul good. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten not for <hi>Conceits,</hi> or the <hi>new notions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="35">35. Take notice of that which concernes your <hi>own condition,</hi> and be not too buſie to marke who elſe is <hi>hit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="36">36. Know that the <hi>Lords Table</hi> hath the beſt <hi>refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> &amp; that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions are moſt whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
               <pb n="229" facs="tcp:54709:120"/>
               <p n="37">37. Learne to diſcerne the <hi>Lords body.</hi> They eate nothing but bread, that want Faith.</p>
               <p n="38">38. Though ye be not <hi>worthy,</hi> yet have a care to behave your ſelves <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily</hi> at <hi>Chriſts</hi> Table.</p>
               <p n="39">39. Keep publike <hi>Faſts,</hi> and publike <hi>Thankſ-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings</hi> with publike ſpirits.</p>
               <p n="40">40. Studie <hi>Communion</hi> with <hi>Saints.</hi> Neglect not to doe, or to receive good in <hi>Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="41">41. Lay out <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> for the mutuall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of each others Faith.</p>
               <p n="42">42. Endeavour <hi>Mortiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> Studie God more,
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:54709:121"/>and the creature leſſe.</p>
               <p n="43">43. <hi>Reade</hi> often, and with judgement. Reade not a <hi>Chapter</hi> only for noveltie; or where the Booke fals open, as if ye hapned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Bible</hi> by chance.</p>
               <p n="44">44. Refer what ye reade to <hi>head's.</hi> Some have much houſe-hold-ſtuffe, but not placed in any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſo no uſe of it.</p>
               <p n="45">45. Reade the <hi>leſſe,</hi> ſo that ye <hi>understand</hi> it; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then much as a meere <hi>taske.</hi> They that <hi>limpe</hi> in the way, goe on more then ſuch as <hi>run</hi> out of the way.</p>
               <p n="46">46. Reade with <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                  <pb n="231" facs="tcp:54709:121"/>Pray in Reading, as well as before. The Spirit of God then will tell you his <hi>own meaning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="47">47. <hi>Meditate.</hi> This meat cannot <hi>digeſt</hi> unleſſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the <hi>Stomack.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="48">48. Seeke <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Word. Seeke the <hi>mind</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="49">49. Reade with Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Conſtancie. It may be the <hi>Silver-veine</hi> will not be found at firſt.</p>
               <p n="50">50. In the whole courſe be <hi>Eaven;</hi> with an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall reſpect to all the <hi>Commandements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is time, to take off my hand from this
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:54709:122"/>Table. And it may be it were beſt to leave this as an <hi>unfiniſhed Piece,</hi> for I confeſſe I am not able to make ſuch a <hi>draught</hi> as I would. I have done to my owne ſatisfaction, if the <hi>colours</hi> of <hi>Holineſse</hi> be moſt <hi>freſh;</hi> for I entended to make the woman that is <hi>Religious,</hi> more lovely, then ſhe that is <hi>modeſt,</hi> or <hi>humble,</hi> or <hi>wiſe.</hi> Thoſe are high Praiſes, but this the higheſt. <hi>Thoſe daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have done vertuouſly, but this excelleth them All.</hi> In a word, That woman is moſt <hi>excellent,</hi> who is <hi>moſt Holy.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
